<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Pulpit-sayings, or, The characters of the pulpit-papist examined in answer to the Apology for the pulpits and in vindication of the representer against the stater of the controversie.</title>
            <author>Gother, John, d. 1704.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 190 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41623</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1347</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18623</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12661936</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12661936</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65446</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41623)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65446)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 355:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Pulpit-sayings, or, The characters of the pulpit-papist examined in answer to the Apology for the pulpits and in vindication of the representer against the stater of the controversie.</title>
                  <author>Gother, John, d. 1704.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[15], 58, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Hills ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by J. Gother; the "stater of the controversie" is W. Clagett. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>"With allowance"</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Preliminary pages dark and partially illegible.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Williams, John, 1636?-1709. --  Apology for the pulpits.</term>
               <term>Clagett, William, 1646-1688.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65446:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> Pulpit-Sayings, OR, THE CHARACTERS OF THE Pulpit-Papiſt EXAMINED.</p>
            <p>IN ANSWER TO THE <hi>Apology for the Pulpits,</hi> AND IN Vindication of the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> againſt the <hi>Stater of the Controverſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>With Allowance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills,</hi> Printer to the King's Moſt Excellent Majeſty, for His Houſhold and Chappel; And are ſold at his Printing-houſe on the Ditch-ſide in <hi>Black-Fryers.</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:65446:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>IF to be a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> is to be that which is deſcrib'd in the following <hi>Characters,</hi> I do here declare, that <hi>I am none:</hi> and that I am ſo far from underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Apologies</hi> for Men of <hi>ſuch Practices</hi> and <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief,</hi> that I here profeſs a hearty deteſtation of all ſuch Engagements. What kind of Religion is it then, that is here ſet forth in theſe <hi>Characters?</hi> I call it <hi>Pulpit-Popery,</hi> and him that profeſſes it, a <hi>Pulpit-Papiſt: that is,</hi> ſuch <hi>Popery,</hi> and ſuch a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> as is deſcrib'd by <hi>Miniſters</hi> in their <hi>Pulpits,</hi> and which the People are taught to purſue with Hatred and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. Well, and am not I then <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and is not my Religion <hi>ſuch Popery?</hi> No, I profeſs, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce <hi>ſuch Popery:</hi> and if there be any <hi>Papiſts</hi> that are taught ſuch a Religion, I here <hi>Proteſt</hi> againſt them. And is it poſſible then, that a <hi>Papiſt</hi> can renounce <hi>Popery?</hi> Yes, any <hi>Papiſt</hi> in Town may ſafely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce this <hi>Pulpit-Popery,</hi> which is ſo unlike the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin</hi> and <hi>Faith</hi> we are <hi>oblig'd</hi> to learn in <hi>our Church,</hi> that whoſoever will be a <hi>good Papiſt</hi> muſt, inſtead of aſſenting to, diſclaim every Point that is here ſet down by the <hi>Pulpits,</hi> as Articles of his Religion.</p>
            <p>But this is a foul Aſperſion, <hi>ſays ſomebody,</hi> and a moſt ſcandalous Reflection upon the <hi>Pulpits,</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, that whilſt they undertake to deſcribe the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:65446:3"/> they aſſert ſuch <hi>Principles</hi> for <hi>Popery,</hi> which the <hi>Papiſts</hi> deteſt as much as they. 'Tis true indeed, I confeſs, 'tis a thing in which they are ſomething con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd: But as long as thoſe <hi>Chairs</hi> pretend to no more than a <hi>Fallibility,</hi> 'tis a thing they themſelves own, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat <hi>they may be miſtaken;</hi> and I go but one Step far<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and <hi>modeſtly</hi> ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n theſe Points relating to the <hi>Papiſts, They are miſtaken.</hi> And pray now, where is the Crime in this? I hope I may be ſuppos'd to know <hi>what my Religion is,</hi> as well as they<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and if they declare to their Congregation, that <hi>our Religion is,</hi> what I know <hi>it is not,</hi> I am bound, in defence of Truth, to declare <hi>They are miſtaken.</hi> I'll tell you, as long as the <hi>Pulpits</hi> employ themſelves in correcting the <hi>Vices</hi> of their Congregation, in teaching them to lead <hi>good Lives,</hi> not to uſe <hi>Frauds,</hi> nor <hi>Cheat,</hi> nor <hi>Lye,</hi> nor <hi>Swear,</hi> nor <hi>Blaſpheme,</hi> to avoid all <hi>Exceſſes,</hi> &amp;c. I commend, I applaud them, I ſpeak all the good things that poſſibly I can of them. As long as they diſcourage thoſe under their Charge, from <hi>Praying to Images;</hi> from <hi>attributing Satisfaction and Expiation to a Crucifix of Wood or Stone,</hi> from <hi>putting any truſt in it;</hi> from <hi>eſteeming every thing good and meritorious, that makes for their Cauſe,</hi> or <hi>for their Church's Intereſt;</hi> from <hi>changing the Scripture into Legends;</hi> from <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Purgatory inſtead of Repentance, Faction inſtead of Faith;</hi> from <hi>the thought of Compounding with Heaven for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nforſaken Sins, of procuring Indulgences for Deadly Sins for many Years to come;</hi> from <hi>Worſhipping Bread and Wine as God himſelf;</hi> from <hi>appearing before God Dumb and Senſleſs, and ſaying their Prayers without Attention;</hi> from <hi>binding themſelves to Ignorance by Vow,</hi> &amp;c. As long, I ſay, as they diſcourage their Flock from theſe <hi>Follies</hi> and <hi>Abominations,</hi> they do
<pb facs="tcp:65446:3"/> exceeding well, they do like Chriſtians, I joyn with them, and deſire them to hold on theſe ſo wholſom Leſſons. Again, as long as they declaim againſt the <hi>Abuſes</hi> of <hi>Relics,</hi> of <hi>Pretended Miracles,</hi> of <hi>Confeſſion;</hi> againſt the <hi>ill Example, ſcandalous Lives, Pride</hi> and <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> of ſome Church-men; againſt <hi>Tyranny, Murder, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation, Cruelty, Oppreſſion, Maſſacres, Plots, Treaſons, Rebellion,</hi> &amp;c. This is ſtill all very well; 'tis what <hi>Catholics</hi> do, and I would do it my ſelf, were I to Preach; I have nothing therefore to ſay againſt the <hi>Pulpits,</hi> whilſt they are engag'd in theſe Subjects, but concur with them with all my heart. But when they take a Step beyond this, and lay all this at the <hi>Papiſts</hi> doors, and deſcribe all theſe <hi>Abſurdities</hi> as the <hi>Religion</hi> of the <hi>Papiſts;</hi> and that to <hi>become a Papiſt,</hi> is to be inſtructed in, and oblig'd to the Profeſſion of all theſe <hi>Monſtrous Abominations;</hi> here I think my <hi>Self</hi> my <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Church</hi> concern'd; and therefore I ſtep in with my <hi>Advice to the Pulpits:</hi> and tho', I confeſs, 'twould be a daring Preſumption in me to pretend to direct them, how they are to Guide and Feed their <hi>own Flock;</hi> yet I take it for no ſuch Crime to put them in mind, that they be not <hi>Injurious to their Neighbor:</hi> This is a <hi>Lecture</hi> all Chriſtians have a <hi>Right</hi> to Preach; and therefore with this Sermon of <hi>Advice</hi> I make up to our <hi>Preachers,</hi> who are ſo forward in making <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters</hi> of the <hi>Papiſts.</hi> I tell them, that tho' they may have but little Affection for the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> yet they ought to be careful, not to be <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt to them,</hi> not to <hi>wrong them</hi> in their Reputation, not to <hi>defame them</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of every <hi>Idle Story,</hi> not to promote <hi>Calumnies,</hi> Preach out of <hi>Narratives,</hi> nor to ſet up every <hi>Miſconſtruction</hi> of their own Phancy, every <hi>Opinion</hi> of Authors, every <hi>Extravagancy</hi> of her Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,
<pb facs="tcp:65446:4"/> for the <hi>Profeſs'd Religion</hi> of the <hi>Papiſts.</hi> This, and much more of this kind, I put them in mind of; and tho' it be ſo truly <hi>Chriſtian Advice,</hi> yet I find they take it unkindly; they are not willing to be thought Men of <hi>ſuch Principles,</hi> as to ſtand in need of this Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. Now, for my part, I never pretended that they were of <hi>ſuch Principles,</hi> as to proceed in this manner, and be ſo unjuſt to the Papiſts <hi>deſignedly:</hi> But alaſs! there's a great deal of Miſchief done in the World, which is never done by <hi>Deſign.</hi> There are ſome little Accidents to which <hi>Frail Human Nature</hi> is very ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, call'd <hi>Paſſion, Prejudice, Prepoſſeſſion, Diſaffecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe are very <hi>inſinuating</hi> things, and of a <hi>treacherous</hi> nature, which put Men upon the worſt of Engagements, and do the greateſt Miſchiefs in the World, without any <hi>open Deſign</hi> of doing any. And therefore, ſince the matter of <hi>Fact</hi> to me is certain, the <hi>Miſchief and Injuſtice done,</hi> and we here ſuppoſe without <hi>Deſign,</hi> I muſt deſire the <hi>Preachers</hi> to reflect, whether none of theſe <hi>Miſchievous Accidents</hi> at leaſt, ever went up with them into the <hi>Pulpit;</hi> whether <hi>Paſſion</hi> and <hi>Animoſity</hi> never crept with them into thoſe <hi>Chairs;</hi> whether <hi>Prejudice</hi> never influenc'd their <hi>Pen</hi> and <hi>Tongue;</hi> whether <hi>Prepoſſeſſion</hi> never biaſs'd their <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Judgment;</hi> and likewiſe, whether they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>rack'd</hi> a <hi>Text,</hi> in compliance with the <hi>Temper</hi> and <hi>Humor</hi> of their Flock. The People, we know, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not always bear the <hi>Truth;</hi> they ſometimes ſay with the <hi>Jews</hi> (Iſa. 30. 10.) <hi>Propheſie not unto us right things; ſpeak unto us ſmooth things, propheſie Deceits:</hi> Did the <hi>Preachers</hi> never follow this <hi>Bent</hi> of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? Come, I wiſh they would make a thorough Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men into themſelves. I fear they are Frail, are under Temptations, and yield to them ſometimes like other
<pb facs="tcp:65446:4"/> Mortals. Where there is ſo much of <hi>Diviſion,</hi> and different <hi>Intereſts,</hi> I ſuſpect all theſe <hi>Evil Qualities</hi> muſt have ſome acceſs: 'twas ever ſo from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning; and I apprehend 'tis from the ill Direction of <hi>theſe,</hi> our Religion has ſuffer'd ſo much. For my part, I ſeldom hear any ſpeak of <hi>Popery</hi> now, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently a <hi>Sour</hi> and <hi>Peeviſh</hi> Temper appears againſt it, and <hi>Sober Reaſon,</hi> which ought to guide every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian in the Concern of Religion, ſeems to be quite laid aſide; and this is a ſign, that the Contention is more for a <hi>Party,</hi> than a Zeal for <hi>Truth,</hi> which needs not the aſſiſtance of theſe Ill Qualities to defend or enlarge its Poſſeſſions. But theſe are only the natural Conſequences of <hi>Diviſion,</hi> which under the Pretext of <hi>Religion,</hi> puts Men upon the moſt unwarrantable Methods both for ſecuring themſelves and defeating their Neighbors. And 'tis not we only that are ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of theſe ill Effects, but others too. And therefore let me here take occaſion more ſolemnly to complain, that ſince the <hi>Pretence</hi> to Religion has torn Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity into <hi>Parties,</hi> Animoſities and Hatred have taken the place of Love and Unity; <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealouſies</hi> have paſs'd for ſolid Reaſon and Judgment; and ſcarce any <hi>one</hi> Body of Chriſtians have been known by <hi>another,</hi> but under <hi>falſe Colours,</hi> and a <hi>baſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe.</hi> Hence it is, that whilſt few diſcover ſcarce any <hi>Beauty</hi> and <hi>Order,</hi> but in their own Communion; and in all others there appears ſo much of the <hi>Monſter,</hi> Heats every where encreaſe, and Men as fiercely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage each other, as if their <hi>Oppoſites</hi> were nothing better than <hi>Turks</hi> or <hi>Infidels;</hi> and the Truth of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity which they ſo earneſtly contend for, is loſt by their uncharitable Diſſentions. The truth of this let every one conſider in their ſeveral Diviſions, and
<pb facs="tcp:65446:5"/> when they have been ſerious a while in this ſo lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table a Proſpect, and view'd the diſtracted State of Chriſtians, let them compare it with the <hi>Command</hi> of Chriſt, of <hi>Love one another;</hi> and <hi>Be ye one, as I and my Father are one:</hi> and if the Sight do's not move to Compaſſion, and engage as many as behold it, to a zealous removal of theſe Differences, 'tis becauſe theſe <hi>Schiſms</hi> have deſtroy'd all <hi>Charity,</hi> and under a falſe Gloſs of <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> have taught Men to forget their Duty both to God and their Neighbor. For my part, I have experienc'd the truth of this in Men of all Perſuaſions in regard to the <hi>Religion</hi> I profeſs. I have heard and ſeen it rail'd at, contemn'd, ſet upon the ſame File with <hi>Turciſm</hi> and <hi>Infidelity,</hi> abandon'd even to the blackeſt Hell; and as many as profeſs it, reputed no better than <hi>Madmen</hi> or <hi>Fools;</hi> and not made the Objects ſo much of <hi>Compaſſion</hi> and <hi>Pity,</hi> as of <hi>Hatred</hi> and <hi>Scorn.</hi> This, I ſay, I have ſeen with a confuſion of Spirit, and deep reſentment of Soul; and wondred, how a <hi>Religion,</hi> by which I had been taught to <hi>Love God and my Neighbor,</hi> and to perform all <hi>Chriſtian Duties,</hi> ſhould by other Chriſtians be render'd ſo <hi>black</hi> and <hi>odious,</hi> and her Doctrins ſo <hi>helliſh</hi> and <hi>damnable.</hi> But this was not long a Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; a little Conſideration ſoon diſcover'd, that 'twas none of <hi>my Religion</hi> was thus hotly decry'd, but a <hi>Monſter of Iniquity</hi> ſet up under her <hi>Name.</hi> And, that tho' her Members were Ridicul'd, Perſecuted and Defam'd, yet 'twas for <hi>Doctrins</hi> they were never taught by her, and for Facts they were either not concern'd in, or not approv'd. And ſo it appear'd that this great diſturbance of Chriſtianity, this effa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing its Beauty, this ſo wide a breach of Charity, this propagating of Diviſions, this inverting the Doctrin
<pb facs="tcp:65446:5"/> of Chriſt, and teaching Men to <hi>hate,</hi> inſtead of <hi>love,</hi> one another, was chiefly occaſion'd by <hi>Miſunderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> by <hi>falſe Dreſſes, counterfeit Colours,</hi> and <hi>imagin'd Monſters</hi> more than <hi>real ones.</hi> And is not this a ſhame to Chriſtendom, that it ſhould be thus torn in pieces for <hi>Dreams</hi> and <hi>Phancies,</hi> to have its Peace bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to fight with <hi>Shadows,</hi> and that Reaſoning Men ſhould, for <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealouſies,</hi> run down the moſt Fundamental <hi>Doctrins</hi> and <hi>Commands</hi> of Chriſt? But there's enough of this; and 'tis time, that as many as pretend to be Followers of Chriſt, ſhould now ſet their Hand to the recovering his Glory, and the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of the <hi>Religion</hi> they profeſs: that we, who own our ſelves oblig'd, to be of <hi>one Mind</hi> and <hi>one Spirit,</hi> to preſerve a mutual <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> may be no longer a Scandal to <hi>Atheiſts, Jews,</hi> and <hi>Turks,</hi> and by our <hi>Diviſions</hi> overthrow that Kingdom, which we all zealouſly pretend to maintain. Since therefore the great occaſion of this Miſchief is, that Chriſtians know not one another; that hence they raiſe to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>Adverſaries</hi> upon <hi>miſtake,</hi> and as fiercely engage them, as if they were <hi>real:</hi> nothing can poſſibly more contribute to the Common Peace and Unity of Chriſtendom, than that every <hi>Diviſion</hi> of <hi>Pretenders</hi> ſhould fairly lay open the Particulars in which they look upon themſelves abus'd, ſhew wherein they are wrong'd, ſo to endeavor the remove of all <hi>Miſunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings</hi> and <hi>Miſtakes.</hi> This, I don't queſtion, would be highly advantageous, for the recovering the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Primitive Believers. And becauſe amongſt all other Communions, that of <hi>Popery</hi> is become the greateſt <hi>Bugbear,</hi> frights People into all the Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies of the Heathens, in defence of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> makes them trample all the <hi>Commands</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> under
<pb facs="tcp:65446:6"/> foot, for the ſupport of Chriſtianity; is reputed the greateſt Aggrievance, the common Seed of Diviſions, and what chiefly ſeems to render all amicable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions impoſſible: I'll endeavor, in order to this General Good, to let the World ſee, 'tis only <hi>Miſtake</hi> or <hi>Paſſion</hi> has made her ſo <hi>deform'd a Monſter;</hi> and that tho' ſhe be commonly <hi>pretended</hi> the <hi>Occaſion</hi> of many <hi>Pagan Proceedings</hi> amongſt <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> 'tis not for what <hi>She really is,</hi> but what <hi>She's made to be</hi> by ſuch unquiet Spirits, who cannot make good their Poſts, and vent their violent Paſſions with Applauſe, unleſs ſet forth under this Cloke of <hi>Religion:</hi> And conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, that were She <hi>truly</hi> known, as to her genuin <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Doctrin,</hi> the greateſt part of our Diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances would be certainly prevented, the Enemies of the Common Peace would be quite diſabled, as to their chiefeſt Engine, and <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> be ſo far re-eſtabliſh'd amongſt us. This every one will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude to be true, who has taken a Proſpect of <hi>Holland,</hi> and thoſe Towns of <hi>Germany,</hi> in which <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants</hi> live together in one Corporation, under the <hi>ſame Laws,</hi> and making uſe in ſome Places even of the <hi>ſame Churches</hi> too; and this with ſuch <hi>Freedom, Amity</hi> and <hi>good Correſpondence,</hi> that their <hi>different Communion,</hi> cannot be eaſily diſcover'd; and a Man that ſhould come out of <hi>England</hi> with his Head glow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with our <hi>Pulpit-Popery,</hi> would not be eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd of the being of any <hi>Papiſts</hi> there. Now 'tis certain, the <hi>Papiſts here</hi> and <hi>there,</hi> are of the ſame <hi>Church, Principles</hi> and <hi>Faith,</hi> and 'tis no Difference in this kind, makes them <hi>there</hi> like <hi>other Men,</hi> and <hi>here</hi> like <hi>Monſters;</hi> but 'tis becauſe <hi>there</hi> the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are what they <hi>are,</hi> and <hi>here</hi> they are made to be what they <hi>are not,</hi> but what their <hi>Maligners</hi> pleaſe to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:65446:6"/> them. And as long as they are only look'd on through this <hi>falſe Glaſs,</hi> and ſhewn to the People un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Deformity of <hi>many Heads</hi> and <hi>Horns,</hi> and with the <hi>Beaſt</hi> all over, what hopes of their being receiv'd into the Bond of <hi>Common Charity?</hi> Or what greater encouragement for Feuds and unchriſtian Animoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, than that <hi>theſe</hi> ſhould be ſo mark'd out for Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> to be purſu'd with Contempt and Hatred by their Neighbors, in the Service and Fear of the Lord? I muſt needs confeſs, that were <hi>Popery</hi> ſo foul, as 'tis in the opinion of the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> were its <hi>Principles ſo cruel and bloody, did it teach Men Idolatry, to worſhip any Creature for God, to neglect the Commandments,</hi> &amp;c. I would chooſe rather to be <hi>Jew, Turk,</hi> or <hi>Infidel,</hi> than a <hi>Papiſt;</hi> I would willingly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to all the Compariſons betwixt <hi>Paganiſm</hi> and <hi>Popery;</hi> I would own, that a Man muſt of neceſſity lay by both <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> before he could take up <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>Religion;</hi> and that to Preach againſt it, and endeavor its ruin, would not be only laudable, but even a <hi>neceſſary Duty.</hi> But if this <hi>black Character</hi> ſhould no otherwiſe agree to it, than by <hi>Miſtake;</hi> if the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſhould not <hi>really</hi> teach nor believe thoſe <hi>Fopperies</hi> and abſurd <hi>Doctrins,</hi> which are laid to them, but utterly abhor and diſclaim them; then 'tis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain our little World has been fill'd with Confuſions upon <hi>Imagination;</hi> it has been frighted into moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accountable Practices, by idle Jealouſies; and there can be no ſurer way for retrieving the paſt, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting all ſuch like Miſchiefs, than by more cloſely examining the thing we fear, and ſeeing whether it be a <hi>real Monſter</hi> we dread, or elſe ſomething <hi>artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally dreſs'd</hi> up for to fright the unwary.</p>
            <p>For my part, I am not aſham'd here to own, that
<pb facs="tcp:65446:7"/> my Religion is <hi>Popery,</hi> as taught and deliver'd by the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> I embrac'd it without the influence of any <hi>Temporal Motive,</hi> and I continue in it, upon the hopes of obtaining Salvation, in the Profeſſion of her <hi>Faith,</hi> and obſervance of her <hi>Doctrins,</hi> through the <hi>Merits</hi> and <hi>Paſſion</hi> of my ever Bleſſed <hi>Redeemer.</hi> And 'twas no ſmall ſurpriſe to me, to hear <hi>this</hi> very <hi>Church,</hi> (the Purity of whoſe Belief and Doctrin I admir'd) ſo poſitively decry'd for the <hi>Whore</hi> of <hi>Babylon,</hi> for the Promoter of all Inhuman Barbarities, rank'd with <hi>Paganiſm</hi> and <hi>Turciſm,</hi> the Prophaner of God's Holy Word, and Propagator of the Doctrin of Devils, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I was alarm'd at this Character, and immediately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, that <hi>if this was ſo,</hi> I had been greatly miſtaken, and inſtead of putting my ſelf into the way of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> had certainly fall'n into the very Mouth of <hi>Hell.</hi> This put me upon ſome Reflections, and oblig'd me to enter into a more ſtrict Scrutiny of my Religion, and my ſelf: I did both with ſeriouſneſs, knowing that the Concern was of <hi>Eternity,</hi> and whereon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended my Soul's Salvation or Damnation. Upon examination of my ſelf, I could not find that, I had been taught any of thoſe Helliſh Doctrins charg'd againſt my <hi>Church;</hi> or that <hi>She</hi> any where deliver'd them: but on the contrary, that I had been directed by Her, <hi>To worſhip and adore one only Living God; To ſerve him with fear and trembling; To love him above all things; To keep his Commandments; To love my Neighbor as my ſelf, and in all things to fulfil the Law of Chriſt; That nothing was ſo contradictory to this Law, as to commit Idolatry, to prophane the Word of God, or any ways to propagate Superſtition, or the Doctrin of Devils; And that I ought rather to ſuffer Death a thouſand times, than once incur the Guilt of any of theſe Crimes.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:65446:7"/> Now here, what could I think, finding my <hi>Church</hi> wholly <hi>oppoſit</hi> to the <hi>Character</hi> given of it; and my ſelf lying under the Scandal of ſuch Doctrins, which I did as much abhor, as Hell and Damnation it ſelf? I was convinc'd of the falſneſs of the Charge, and that the Accuſation was a <hi>Calumny;</hi> but whether proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from <hi>Miſtake, Miſunderſtanding, Ignorance, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, Intereſt, Paſſion,</hi> or <hi>Malice,</hi> I was not able to determine. But a farther enquiry into the Proofs, produc'd for the making good this Charge, gave me ſome ſatisfaction: For here amongſt theſe, I found a great number of Matters of <hi>Fact,</hi> as <hi>Maſſacres, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations, Murders of Princes, Treaſons, Plots, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies, Perſecutions,</hi> and other ſuch unwarrantable Practices, charg'd againſt the Members of this <hi>Church.</hi> I found again the vicious and ſcandalous Lives of ſome of her chief Prelates, their <hi>Pride, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Luxury,</hi> laid home; as likewiſe the ill Examples of other Eccleſiaſtical Dignitaries, as of <hi>Cardinals, Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>Prieſts;</hi> their <hi>Ignorance, Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, Oppreſſion, Cruelties, Exceſſes,</hi> &amp;c. Then the <hi>looſe</hi> and <hi>extravagant</hi> Opinions of many of her <hi>Doctors.</hi> Laſtly, many Superſtitions and Abuſes found amongſt the People, their being impos'd on by ſome with idle Inventions, the noiſe of Relics and Miracles, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prieſt-ridden a thouſand other ways. Theſe I ſay, I found, with others of the ſame blackneſs urg'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Men in Communion with my <hi>Church.</hi> And hence a Concluſion drawn upon the <hi>whole Church,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her <hi>Doctrin,</hi> and all in her Communion, of <hi>their being as foul as Hell, of the ſame Tincture with theſe Villanies and Crimes.</hi> And here it was I began to lay aſide all Troubles and Scruples concerning my Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, being now well ſatisfi'd, that the frightful <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:65446:8"/> of my <hi>Church,</hi> whlch ſurpris'd me before, was not taken from her <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Doctrin,</hi> but only from the Vice and Wickedneſs of ſuch, who tho' perchance in her Communion, yet follow'd not her Direction: and that 'twas rather a black Record of as many vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanous Practices, as had ever been committed by any of her Members, Shamm'd upon the People for a Draught of ſuch things the <hi>Church taught, encourag'd,</hi> and <hi>approv'd.</hi> And here upon the whole, I could not but lament theſe uncharitable Proceedings, to ſee ſo great a Body of Believers, ſuch an infinit number of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, of which I was one, lie under ſo baſe, ſo ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous a Reproach, to ſee them condemn'd for the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bettors of ſuch <hi>Principles</hi> which they deteſted and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horr'd; and the <hi>Crimes</hi> of their Anceſtors made to be their <hi>Religion.</hi> For my part, this Method appear'd to me much beneath all Reaſon and Religion. I thought, if this were once allowable and juſt, we might all be Indicted for Felons and Horſe-ſtealers, becauſe many of our Church had been convicted of thoſe Crimes; that the Debaucheries of the <hi>Stews, Whitefriers</hi> and the <hi>Mint,</hi> might be prov'd to be <hi>according to Precept;</hi> and the <hi>Rules</hi> of Chriſtianity be exactly drawn, by the <hi>Offences</hi> of thoſe that <hi>tranſgreſs</hi> them. I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, had I, upon examination, found, I had been taught by my <hi>Religion,</hi> or of my ſelf approv'd thoſe <hi>Villanies,</hi> for which, under the name of <hi>Papiſt,</hi> I, with all of my Communion have ſuffered in our Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I ſhould own all as <hi>Juſt</hi> and <hi>Deſerv'd:</hi> but ſince we, as <hi>Papiſts,</hi> have always before God, and are ready before Men, to diſclaim and utterly renounce all ſuch <hi>Facts</hi> and <hi>Principles,</hi> without the leaſt Injury to our <hi>Religion,</hi> whatſoever we ſuffer on this ſcore, cannot be, but as much againſt <hi>Juſtice,</hi> againſt <hi>Charity,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:65446:8"/> againſt <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> as againſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s:</hi> and the very <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> themſelves might upon as good reaſon be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd of all the <hi>Abuſes</hi> and <hi>Errors</hi> of their <hi>Reprobate</hi> Brethren, as we of all the <hi>Crimes</hi> and <hi>Fopperies</hi> pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis'd by Extravagant Men of our <hi>Church.</hi> I cannot therefore, conſidering how damnable a Sin <hi>Calumny</hi> is, and the defaming a vaſt Society of Chriſtians with the moſt infamous of Crimes, I cannot, I ſay, but have ſo much Charity for the moſt violent of our Oppoſers, as to think, that did they but believe us <hi>Innocent</hi> in theſe Reſpects, they would no longer purſue us with ſuch Infamy and Reproach: and conſequently that a great reaſon why we are thrown out by ſo many, from the number of Chriſtians, and degraded by others amongſt Turks and Infidels, by others condemn'd for Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, by others reputed as Bloody and Barbarous, by others as Ideots and Mad, by others as Blind and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, by others as Ignorant as Aſſes, Horſes, and Mules, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is becauſe, <hi>they know not what we are, what we Teach, nor what we Believe;</hi> becauſe they take the <hi>Offences</hi> of <hi>ſome</hi> of our Members, for the <hi>Religion</hi> of <hi>all;</hi> the <hi>Opinions</hi> of <hi>ſome Caſuiſts,</hi> for the <hi>Doctrin</hi> of the <hi>Church;</hi> the <hi>Vices</hi> of <hi>Men,</hi> for the <hi>Rules</hi> of the <hi>Society; Abuſes</hi> for <hi>Directions,</hi> and <hi>Superſtitions</hi> for <hi>Duties.</hi> What therefore can we more commendably do, for the Good of Chriſtianity, than to diſabuſe our Brethren, remove the occaſion of our ſo many years Diſturbances, and ſettle a right Underſtanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween all thoſe who believe, there's <hi>no Salvation,</hi> where there's <hi>no Charity.</hi> This I have already endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor'd in ſome plain and ſhort Tracts, not long ſince Publiſh'd; I'll here go on to wipe off ſuch <hi>Scandals</hi> as have been urg'd againſt us from the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> which if done ſeriouſly, may ſtill contribute to the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:65446:9"/> end, and make it appear, the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are none of the <hi>Monſters</hi> they are imagin'd. This I'll do, by Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſuch <hi>Characters,</hi> as have been of late Years given of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> from the <hi>Pulpits.</hi> In which I ſhall ſhew, that there are many things charg'd upon them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either Truth or Sincerity; and conſequently, that 'tis not without good Grounds they complain of being <hi>Miſrepreſented.</hi> But firſt I muſt have a word or two with a late Adverſary, and then to the <hi>Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters</hi> of the <hi>Pulpit-Papiſt.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65446:9"/>
            <head>Pulpit-Sayings, OR, THE CHARACTERS OF A Pulpit-Papiſt EXAMINED.</head>
            <p>FOR the bringing the long Debate of <hi>Miſrepreſenting</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pref. to Third Part of Pap. Miſrep.</note> to an iſſue, I lately made a <hi>Challenge</hi> to the <hi>Pulpits</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to ſhew us the <hi>Papiſts</hi> to be like thoſe <hi>Foul Characters,</hi> that for ſo many years had been given of them from thoſe <hi>High Places.</hi> And tho' the <hi>Preface,</hi> wherein that <hi>Challenge</hi> was publiſh'd, was pretended to be Anſwer'd by one, who, beſides the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent he has of Railing with a good Grace, has likewiſe ſo vain a Conceit of himſelf, as to think he Anſwers <hi>every Line</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anſw. to Repr. Reflect. upon the State of Controv. p.</hi> 5.</note> of his Adverſary; yet when he comes to this <hi>Challenge,</hi> tho' ſo Conſiderable, and whereon depends the Proof of the <hi>Pulpit-Credit,</hi> after having repeated it, and Blazon'd it in Great Characters, he gravely nick-names it with the Title of a <hi>Shout</hi> and an <hi>Exclamation,</hi> pag. 26. and then tamely lets it ſlip betwixt his Fingers; complaining in his next Page, <hi>He can meet with nothing worth the Anſwering.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:65446:10"/>
            <p> How can a Man forbear ſtanding here a little to admire the Contrivance of ſome Men, who, when they are preſs'd with the Difficulty, have not <hi>Humility</hi> enough to own it; but like the Executioners of S. <hi>Stephen,</hi> fly to their laſt Refuge, taking up <hi>Stones</hi> to fling at their Adverſary, when they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not come up to him with a juſt Reply? I appeal here to the Unprejudic'd and Thinking part of Mankind; when the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie of <hi>Miſrepreſenting</hi> was like to grow endleſs, what could be more fairly propos'd, than to require of the <hi>Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits,</hi> to make it appear, <hi>That the Papiſts do in all things anſwer the Character they had given of them?</hi> The bringing this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal to an iſſue, would certainly have concluded the Point. If the <hi>Papiſts</hi> had appear'd to have been <hi>really</hi> what they had been rendred; the <hi>Pulpits</hi> had been acquitted of the Charge: and if it had prov'd otherwiſe, they muſt as certainly been condemn'd as Guilty; and <hi>Miſrepreſenting</hi> muſt have laid at their doors. All the World knows, that the only way to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover whether thoſe, who pretend to ſhew <hi>Strange</hi> and <hi>Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Monſters</hi> to the World, are <hi>Honeſt</hi> Men or <hi>Impoſtors,</hi> is to go into the Booth, and ſee, whether what they have to ſhew there, agrees with their <hi>Deſcriptions</hi> and <hi>Painted Cloths,</hi> which are expos'd on the outſide. If it be every way alike, they muſt have the Repute of <hi>Fair-dealers:</hi> but, if upon the trial, it anſwers not the expectation, and there's no more of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> to be found, beſides in the outſide <hi>Painting</hi> and in <hi>Words;</hi> the <hi>Shewers</hi> muſt certainly paſs for no better than <hi>Cheats;</hi> and that for want of an honeſter Livelihood, they choſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>Impoſe</hi> upon their Neighbor, than <hi>Starve.</hi> Such a Trial as this, was the only Means left, after ſo much <hi>Shifting</hi> and <hi>Winding,</hi> to bring our Controverſie to an iſſue. The <hi>Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits</hi> had been for many years making <hi>Characters</hi> of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and telling the World, how <hi>Strange</hi> and <hi>Deform'd Monſters</hi> they were. The <hi>Truth</hi> of <hi>their Characters</hi> was at length que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion'd, and the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are ſaid, not to agree with thoſe <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd Features,</hi> nor be the <hi>Monſters</hi> they had been pretended. And here began the Difference: the one Side <hi>poſitively deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> the other as <hi>ſtiffly aſſerting</hi> the <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Exactneſs</hi> of the <hi>Characters.</hi> What was to be done here, beſide making the Experiment? Come therefore, ſaid I to the <hi>Pulpits,</hi> (and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:65446:10"/> withal gave them the <hi>Challenge)</hi> Shew us the <hi>Papiſts</hi> to agree with your Characters; let us ſee them: and then without any farther trouble we ſhall know, whether the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are really the <hi>Monſters</hi> you decipher'd them; or You <hi>Impoſtors,</hi> for expoſing them otherwiſe than They were. This <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge</hi> I made; and tho' the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> is ſo throughly acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with <hi>Monſters,</hi> as to know them to be very <hi>Remarkable things, and may be ſhewn with a Finger, ib. p.</hi> 36. yet ho's ſo far from joyning iſſue with me here, that tho' the Deciſion de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended upon ſo inconſiderable a Matter, as the <hi>holding forth a Finger</hi> and <hi>Pointing,</hi> he'll not vouchſafe the trouble; but inſtead of that, lifts up both his Hands againſt me, and by moſt <hi>vile and baſe Innuendo's, p.</hi> 27. ſhews how <hi>low</hi> he can ſtoop, only for the poor ſatisfaction of taking up <hi>Dirt</hi> to throw at his Adverſary. Certainly the Cauſe muſt be very deſperate, that is thus deſerted, and left only with the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of <hi>Railery</hi> and <hi>Reviling.</hi> But 'twas by the help of theſe excellent Qualities, <hi>Miſrepreſenting</hi> at firſt receiv'd a <hi>Being;</hi> and upon theſe Legs it is like to ſtand. Thus is it left by this its <hi>Preſent Patron,</hi> who ſolemnly takes his leave, and bids the Cauſe farewel, as he ſays, <hi>Two</hi> or <hi>Three</hi> had done before him.</p>
            <p>The Challenge therefore I made formerly, for the ending this Controverſie, I here repeat again, not to him, but to all the <hi>Miniſters,</hi> nay to all the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of this Nation: <hi>Shew us the Papiſts to agree with thoſe Characters, that have been given of them out of the Pulpits.</hi> There are few <hi>Miniſters,</hi> but have ſome <hi>Papiſts</hi> in their Pariſh: and few <hi>Lay-men</hi> of any Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but have ſome <hi>Relations, Neighbors, Correſpondents, Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance,</hi> or <hi>Converſation</hi> with ſome <hi>Papiſts.</hi> What I require of them then is, to compare theſe <hi>Papiſts</hi> they know, with the <hi>Idea's, Notions</hi> and <hi>Characters</hi> of the <hi>Pulpit-Papiſt,</hi> that is, with the <hi>Notions</hi> of <hi>Popery</hi> that have been infus'd into them from the <hi>Pulpit.</hi> Let 'em tell me, upon due Conſideration, whether the <hi>Papiſts</hi> they know, are ſo much worſe than all the reſt of Mankind, as the <hi>Pulpits</hi> ſeem to render them. Let them take a view, and ſee, whether the <hi>Papiſts</hi> of their Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance are <hi>ſo profoundly Ignorant, ſo Treacherous,</hi> ſo <hi>Cruel</hi> and <hi>Bloody, ſo Falſe and Deceitful, ſo ready to take Oaths and</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:65446:11"/> 
               <hi>raſhly to break them again, ſo ſtupid and ſenſleſs at their Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, of ſuch profligate Lives, ſo ſtupid as to Pray to Images or Crucifixes, ſo much relying on a Death-bed Repentance.</hi> Let 'em conſider this, I ſay; and if the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are generally found to agree with theſe kind of <hi>Pulpit-Characters,</hi> then the <hi>Pulpits</hi> are in the right: but if it appear, that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are found as free from theſe Imputations, as any other Diviſion of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd Chriſtians;</hi> then the <hi>Pulpits</hi> are in the wrong, and have ſo much Satisfaction to make, as there are <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering in their <hi>Reputation</hi> and <hi>Family,</hi> for the undeſerv'd Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters that have been thus caſt upon them from the <hi>Pulpits.</hi> This is the Challenge I make, and I beg of every <hi>Conſcientious Proteſtant</hi> to make the Reflection. If the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are in good earneſt <hi>more Wicked</hi> and <hi>Extravagant</hi> than their Neighbors, they ſhall not have me to Apologize for them: but if they are really as <hi>Conſcientious,</hi> as <hi>tender</hi> of their <hi>Duty</hi> both to <hi>God</hi> and their <hi>Neighbor,</hi> and as <hi>careful</hi> of their <hi>Salvation</hi> as other Men, 'tis but a Duty to ſpeak in their behalf, and it ſhall not be the <hi>Reproches</hi> of <hi>Two</hi> or <hi>Three</hi> Abuſive Writers, that ſhall deter me from ſo Juſt an Enterpriſe.</p>
            <p>I invite <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to make this Reflection now, becauſe the <hi>Trial</hi> is not ſo difficult at preſent, as it has been in times paſt, when the <hi>Pulpits,</hi> with all the bitterneſs imaginable, were ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> under all the <hi>diſagreeing Colours</hi> of <hi>Monſter</hi> and <hi>Deformity,</hi> and might reaſonably then hope to paſs for <hi>True Repreſenters,</hi> whilſt the <hi>State</hi> at the ſame time was ſo ſevere as to keep them under, and with eſpecial Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo's took care, they ſhould be poſſeſs'd of no <hi>Puhlic Stations,</hi> wherein to ſhew themſelves to the World. At this time 'twas ſafe for the <hi>Pulpits,</hi> to ſay any thing of the <hi>Papiſts;</hi> they might ſet as many Heads and Horns on them as they pleas'd. For whilſt a Man keeps his <hi>Monſter</hi> from being ſeen, he may ſet him out as incredibly Monſtrous as he will, without dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of being diſprov'd. But now, Bleſſed be God, the Times are more open; there's a Liberty for all <hi>Honeſt</hi> Men to ſhew themſelves to the World: and <hi>Papiſts</hi> too, thro' the Favor of their Prince, go Sharers with their Neighbors in every De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree; they have their <hi>Public Poſts</hi> both in the Adminiſtration of the <hi>Sword,</hi> and the <hi>Scale;</hi> and he that has a mind to know,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:65446:11"/> what the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are, has now, God be prais'd, better Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities of doing it, than by going to the Church. At this time then it is, I deſire all ſorts of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> whether <hi>Clergy</hi> or <hi>Laity,</hi> to make the <hi>Trial,</hi> and Anſwer the <hi>Challenge.</hi> There are none, but what upon a ſhort Recollection, may remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, what kind of <hi>Papiſts</hi> they are, they have ſeen ſo often buffeted upon the <hi>Cuſhion;</hi> how much worſe than all the reſt of the World; how ſilly, how <hi>Ridiculous,</hi> how <hi>Faithleſs,</hi> how much better <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are the <hi>Turk</hi> and the <hi>Jew</hi> than <hi>They.</hi> Let them take this <hi>Pulpit-Draught</hi> along with them, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare it with all the <hi>Papiſts</hi> they know, or can hear of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> let them ſee, whether They anſwer the <hi>Character.</hi> And if they find them in all things like the reſt of Mankind, without more <hi>Horns</hi> or <hi>Heads,</hi> let them then tell me, who are the <hi>Miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For my own part, I have heretofore upon occaſion made a like Offer to ſome <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Acquaintance, when I have ſeen them come from <hi>Church,</hi> with their Heads full of <hi>Pulpit-Popcry,</hi> and their Hearts embitter'd againſt it. I have upon this took the liberty of demanding of them, Whether ſuch <hi>Neighbors</hi> of theirs, whom they knew to be <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and with whom they were throughly acquainted, were in reality ſuch Ill-men, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to thoſe Characters of <hi>Popery</hi> they had heard in their Church-Lectures? And they anſwer'd me, <hi>No: but that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> their Conſcience, they judg'd them to be very good Neighbors, and good Chriſtians: and that, if all the reſt were like them, there would be no reaſon to complain.</hi> This Anſwer I have heard at all ends of the Town; ſo that tho' the generality of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are ſo Biaſs'd and <hi>Pulpit-ridden,</hi> that they have an Animoſity againſt the <hi>Papiſts;</hi> yet I find, 'tis not founded upon any <hi>knowledge</hi> of their own, but meerly taken up upon <hi>Truſt;</hi> and and like all other Paſſions, is blindly hurried on againſt ſuch, as they know nothing of. Such a Hood-wink'd Paſſion it was of a Perſon in the Country not long ſince, who loudly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming againſt the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> for a <hi>Generation of Vipers, and a Proſtigate ſort of Men,</hi> &amp;c. after having pour'd forth his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vectives in the bittereſt manner he could, was ask'd by one of the Company, <hi>How many Papiſts he knew?</hi> He reply'd, He knew but <hi>Two Families;</hi> ſuch a Gentleman in ſuch a Place,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65446:12"/> and ſuch another. And it being demanded, <hi>What kind of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons they were?</hi> He ſaid, that Thoſe indeed were <hi>very good Men, Juſt, Honeſt,</hi> and <hi>Exemplar:</hi> but however, that he was ſure the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> at leaſt all the reſt of them, were the worſt of Men. How! ſays the other, You that know but <hi>Two Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies</hi> in the World <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and thoſe <hi>Good beyond Exception;</hi> and yet thus ſeverely to let fly at all the reſt, of whom you know nothing, is an unpardonable Raſhneſs. But this is to the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Tune:</hi> if a Man can't tell how to run down <hi>Popery,</hi> tho' he knows nothing of it, he's no <hi>True Son of the Church of England.</hi> So that tho' the Teachers of this Communion as Eſtabliſh'd by Law, are very induſtrious to diſſuade their Hearers from all <hi>Implicit Faith,</hi> in aſſenting to <hi>Divine Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> deliver'd by the Church; but that they muſt be ſure, not to move one Step beyond their own <hi>Senſe and Reaſon,</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they'll <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot believe like <hi>Men,</hi> but pin their Faith on other Mens Sleeves, and blindly be led by the Noſe; Yet when they turn on the other S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e to hear <hi>what Popery and the Papiſts are;</hi> here they may run o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as <hi>blindly</hi> as they pleaſe, an <hi>Implicit Faith</hi> is now more to the purpoſe: Upon this <hi>Implicit Faith</hi> they may <hi>Hate</hi> them; on this they may <hi>Rail</hi> againſt them: 'Tis not now here, <hi>Search</hi> and <hi>Examin,</hi> and then <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve</hi> and <hi>Speak</hi> as far as by your own knowledge you find to be True: But a <hi>Genuine Son of the Church of England,</hi> is to have a good Stock of this <hi>Implicit Faith</hi> by him, and to <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve</hi> and <hi>Speak,</hi> tho' he knows nothing at all. And this it is I have often obſerv'd, that Thoſe who are the greateſt Begots, and rail moſt bitterly againſt the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> are They that know the leaſt of them, not ſo much as my <hi>Country-man</hi> above, not <hi>Two Families.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But why this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>neven</hi> kind of Dealing in Men that pretend to ſo much <hi>Conſcience</hi> and <hi>Reaſon!</hi> If a Member of the Church of <hi>England</hi> muſt not aſſent to any <hi>Myſtery</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> upon an <hi>Implicit Faith,</hi> for fear of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmanning</hi> himſelf forſooth: why ſhould he ſo unworthily betray his own Reaſon, in taking up <hi>Calumnies</hi> upon <hi>Truſt</hi> for the ruining his Neighbor? As if the believing raſhly of <hi>God</hi> or of our <hi>Neighbor,</hi> were not both deſtructive, and to be avoided by every good Chriſtian. For my part, all that I pretend to here is, that all <hi>Good Proteſtant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:65446:12"/> would obſerve the <hi>Rule</hi> ſo often preſcrib'd from the <hi>Pulpits,</hi> of <hi>Search</hi> and <hi>Examin;</hi> That they would <hi>Try</hi> and <hi>ſee, what the Papiſts are,</hi> before they condemn them. But 'tis not in the <hi>Pamphlets, Books</hi> and <hi>Sermons</hi> of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> I would have them ſeek for this Information; for all theſe I look on only as ſo many <hi>Painted Cloths</hi> or <hi>Popular Harangues,</hi> deſign'd for the making of <hi>Crowds,</hi> and encreaſing the number of <hi>Admirers:</hi> No; what need of taking it thus upon <hi>Truſt,</hi> when, at this time, there are none, but who have opportunity enough, of <hi>ſeeing</hi> and <hi>knowing</hi> the <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves, and letting their own <hi>Eyes,</hi> their own <hi>Ears</hi> tell them, what the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are, inſtead of going to a <hi>Lecture,</hi> and receiving it upon <hi>Truſt</hi> from thoſe, who at the ſame time they are telling, <hi>what the Papiſts are,</hi> are informing their Auditory, how ſilly and unreaſonable a thing it is, to take things <hi>upon Truſt,</hi> and to be contented with an <hi>Implicit Faith,</hi> when they may with much more Security fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their own <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> their own <hi>Eyes</hi> and their <hi>Ears?</hi> 'Tis thus then I deſire <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſhould be try'd, after the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Way;</hi> I would have every one <hi>examin</hi> and <hi>ſee, what the Papiſts are,</hi> with whom they <hi>Converſe,</hi> with whom they <hi>Trade</hi> or have any <hi>Dealing;</hi> ſuch as are of their <hi>Acquaintance</hi> or <hi>Neighborhood;</hi> conſider and reflect on thoſe, who are in any <hi>Public Poſt,</hi> let them uſe all their <hi>Senſes</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and ſtrictly look into their Way of <hi>Living,</hi> and <hi>Dying,</hi> their <hi>Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> the <hi>Care</hi> and <hi>Pains</hi> they take in order to <hi>Salvation:</hi> and then let them ſpeak freely upon their <hi>own knowledge,</hi> whether the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are generally the worſt of their Neighborhood, whether they are <hi>leſs Conſcientious, leſs Humble, leſs Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table,</hi> &amp;c. than others of any other Perſuaſion. But eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially let them have a particular regard to ſuch as are <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts</hi> to the <hi>Catholic Communion,</hi> and obſerve them with a watchful Eye: 'tis certain, if <hi>Popery</hi> be as <hi>Black</hi> as 'tis Paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſo many Degrees worſe than <hi>Proteſtantiſm,</hi> 'twill be impoſſible for a Man, of <hi>Proteſtant</hi> to become <hi>Papiſt,</hi> but 'twill ſoon be diſcover'd in the Immorality of his Life and Actions. Let theſe <hi>Converts</hi> therefore be rigorouſly obſerv'd, to ſee, whether with the <hi>change</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> they change their <hi>Lives</hi> too for the worſt, and appear under all thoſe <hi>Foul Colours,</hi> that are pretended to belong to <hi>Popery.</hi> Let
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:65446:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:65446:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:65446:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:65446:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:65446:15"/> them ſee in particular, whether, upon being <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and going to <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> they are now <hi>leſs ſcrupulous</hi> of offending God, and <hi>more Debauch'd</hi> than they were before; as 'tis ſaid of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Sermons, <hi>viz. That Confeſſion tends</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Good Advice to Pulp. p.</hi> 53. <hi>Anſwer to it,</hi> p. 21, 25.</note> 
               <hi>to the Debauching both Laity and Clergy: and that the Papiſts make no other uſe of Confeſſion, than what profeſs'd Drunkards do of Vomiting.</hi> Let 'em ſee whether they take leſs care of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting, than they did before, or <hi>Sin</hi> now <hi>more confidently,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming upon <hi>Popes Pardons,</hi> and <hi>Compounding</hi> with Heaven for <hi>Money:</hi> Whether they are <hi>leſs Attentive</hi> at their <hi>Prayers; Dumb</hi> and <hi>Senſleſs,</hi> like <hi>Idols,</hi> at their <hi>Devotions</hi> in the Church: Whether they are ſo ſtupid, as to <hi>Pray to Images;</hi> To change <hi>Scripture</hi> into <hi>Legends;</hi> To neglect <hi>Repentance,</hi> becauſe of <hi>Purgatory;</hi> To eſteem every thing <hi>Meritorious</hi> that is for the <hi>Church's Intereſt,</hi> &amp;c. Let all <hi>Converts</hi> be ſtrictly obſerv'd as to theſe and ſuch like Points, which are the common <hi>Pulpit-Characters</hi> of <hi>Popery:</hi> If it be true, what is thus ſolemnly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, with the <hi>Bible in Hand,</hi> the Truth of it muſt neceſſarily appear; for theſe are not <hi>meer Speculations,</hi> confin'd within the <hi>Heart</hi> and <hi>Head:</hi> but they are ſuch <hi>Principles</hi> as influence the <hi>outward Man,</hi> and muſt indiſpenſably regulate the <hi>Actions</hi> of ones Life: ſo that if this be the common Doctrine of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery,</hi> 'twill be impoſſible for ſo many <hi>Profeſſors</hi> of that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, every where to be found, and not to diſcover ſuch an abominable Belief of their Heart, in the common Practice of their Lives.</p>
            <p>Since therefore we are come to things of <hi>Practice</hi> and <hi>Fact,</hi> of which every Man's <hi>own Eyes</hi> and <hi>Ears</hi> may be Judge; I challenge <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in their <hi>own Way:</hi> I appeal from the <hi>Pulpits</hi> to the <hi>Pews,</hi> and inſtead of <hi>Implicit Faith</hi> pinn'd on the <hi>Pulpits,</hi> require the <hi>People</hi> to make uſe of their own <hi>Senſes.</hi> To theſe we are contented to ſtand, and to <hi>their</hi> Arbitration to refer all the Debate of <hi>Miſrepreſenting.</hi> If our <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Actions,</hi> our <hi>Converſation, Living</hi> and <hi>Dying,</hi> are ſo <hi>much worſe</hi> than all the reſt of our Neighbors, anſwerable to what we are accus'd of from the <hi>Pulpits;</hi> We are <hi>deſervedly</hi> evil ſpoken of; and for my part, I ſhall willingly receive the Sentence, of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving my Hands ty'd, from ever Penning any thing for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in favor of a People of ſuch <hi>pernicious Principles,</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:65446:15"/> 
               <hi>Practices;</hi> and the Church of <hi>England</hi> I'll own acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the Charge of <hi>Miſrepreſenting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in this Appeal, I cannot expect, that there ſhall be none <hi>Wicked</hi> or <hi>Scandalous</hi> found in our Communion; 'tis well known, that the Perfecteſt of Creatures, the very <hi>Angels</hi> in Heaven, could not pretend to this, while <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion</hi> infected ſuch vaſt numbers of thoſe Celeſtial Spirits: a <hi>Traitor</hi> too, we know, was found in the very <hi>School</hi> of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> and as long as the <hi>Church Militant</hi> is made up of <hi>Men,</hi> 'tis not to be expected, that a <hi>Right Faith</hi> ſhall ſo privilege them, as that none ſhall be Tempted and Miſled to Evil. All that I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to is, that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are not ſo <hi>infamouſly worſe</hi> than all <hi>other Chriſtians,</hi> as the <hi>Pulpits</hi> ſeem generally to render them: that they live as <hi>Conſcientiouſly,</hi> as <hi>Vertuouſly,</hi> as <hi>fearful of Offending,</hi> as <hi>ſolicitous of Repenting,</hi> &amp;c. as any other <hi>Diviſion,</hi> who pretend to have <hi>Reform'd</hi> them: and conſequently, that their <hi>Doctrins</hi> and <hi>Principles,</hi> by which they regulate their Lives, are not ſuch as they are <hi>Repreſented.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither do I expect, that amongſt ſuch an infinite number of <hi>Writers,</hi> whoſe Works are extant of that Communion, there ſhall be nothing found obnoxious to Exceptions of the Reader, and which may not eaſily, by the help of a wreſted Interpretation, be made appear, in ſeeming <hi>Inferences</hi> plauſibly drawn from it, as Unchriſtian as the Text of the <hi>Alcoran.</hi> All this, I am ſenſible, may without difficulty be found. But this do's not reach the Point; ſince, if this were a juſt Method of ſetting forth any Body of Chriſtians, 'tis certain, there is not at preſent, nor ever was, any Society embodied under that Name, whoſe <hi>Writings</hi> are in every Particular ſo <hi>Exact,</hi> and <hi>cautiouſly</hi> Penn'd, but that by the Artifice of <hi>Envious Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tics,</hi> they might be eaſily defam'd as Prophane, and Impious. I don't queſtion, but if thoſe very <hi>Heads</hi> and <hi>Hands,</hi> that have been ſo induſtrious, for theſe Hundred and fifty years, in ſift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and raking the Books of <hi>Catholics,</hi> had apply'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, with the Encouragement of a like <hi>Malice</hi> and <hi>Intereſt,</hi> to the <hi>Writings</hi> of the <hi>Holy Fathers,</hi> nay of the very <hi>Apoſtles</hi> themſelves, they had as certainly before this time have made them as <hi>Black</hi> as the <hi>Papiſts;</hi> and convinc'd their Followers, Men of an <hi>Implicit Faith,</hi> of the Chriſtian Obligation they were
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:65446:16"/> under, of hating all alike. When once Men come to <hi>Raiſe up</hi> themſelves, by <hi>Running down</hi> their Neighbor, and work their Ends by <hi>Finding fault, Cenſuring, Condemning, Expoſing, Ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> and <hi>Railing</hi> at others, 'tis eaſie to conceive, how Ingenious <hi>Corrupt</hi> Nature will be in ſuch an Undertaking, eſpecially too, when a <hi>pretended Duty</hi> ſtrikes in with this <hi>Vicious Inclination,</hi> and ſpurs it on in its own courſe, 'tis then <hi>Down-hill</hi> all the way, and 'tis hurried along impetuouſly, carrying all before it. Now what will not <hi>Ten thouſand Pulpits,</hi> open every Week, do in this Caſe? What <hi>Lives ſo Holy,</hi> what <hi>Doctrin ſo Divine,</hi> what <hi>Writings ſo Orthodox,</hi> as to ſtand this Teſt? When the Buſineſs of ſo many <hi>Pulpits</hi> is chiefly to <hi>make Exceptions, pick Holes, Quarrel, Ridicule:</hi> and the more excellent they are at this Work, the more they gain upon their Auditory, the more they ſecure their own Intereſt, and prepare themſelves for Honors and Preferments. A little Stock of Conſideration will convince a Man, how much may be done by this kind of <hi>Repreſenting:</hi> ſince whoſoever will but take the pains to view the admirable Effects of it, may be ſatisfi'd, that there has not been any one thing ſo <hi>Sacred,</hi> no <hi>Duty</hi> ſo <hi>Fundamental,</hi> no <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation</hi> ſo <hi>Indiſpenſable,</hi> but what has been vilely trampled on, and expos'd under the blackeſt Colours of <hi>Infamy</hi> and <hi>Irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</hi> 'Tis well known, how even <hi>Innocence</hi> it ſelf heretofore appear'd <hi>defil'd</hi> in <hi>Suſanna,</hi> by the wicked Contrivance of the <hi>Two Elders:</hi> How the <hi>Lamb of God</hi> our Bleſſed <hi>Redeemer</hi> was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd under the Reproaches of a <hi>Deceiver</hi> and <hi>Seditious:</hi> How the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Primitive Chriſtians</hi> were made <hi>Odious</hi> by the malicious Policy of the Prieſts of the <hi>Jews</hi> and the <hi>Heathens:</hi> From whence 'tis certain, there's no Chriſtianity, no Piety, no Perfection, whether in Doctrin or Practice, but what may be vilifi'd and made contemptible by this Art of Deceivers.</p>
            <p>Since therefore, as 'tis evident, the beſt of things may be thus diſguis'd by Adverſaries, and made appear quite different from what they are in themſelves, which I call <hi>Miſrepreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> and this, we ſay, is the Caſe of <hi>Popery</hi> and the <hi>Papiſts;</hi> For the clearing of this Point, I appeal from the Characters of <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Adverſaries, to the very <hi>Lives</hi> of <hi>Papiſts</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. This will be the faireſt Deciſion of the Controverſie, and not ſubject to thoſe many Frauds, which <hi>Intereſt, Ill-will</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:65446:16"/> and <hi>Ignorance</hi> are apt to make uſe of in the other way: Which too, beſides other Inconveniences, is never like to bring the Matter to an iſſue. For whilſt We, in our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, produce <hi>Inſtances</hi> on the one Side, wherein we are <hi>Abus'd, Calumniated,</hi> and <hi>Miſrepreſented:</hi> and our Adverſaries on the other, are <hi>Expounding, Proving,</hi> and <hi>Shifting</hi> the Charge; what likelihood of an end? Since he muſt be tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly dull, even a ſeven-fold-skull'd Man, who when he is accus'd of wronging his Neighbor in an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt Charge,</hi> can't find a <hi>plauſible Pretence</hi> for what he has ſaid, and get off one way or another; eſpecially too, when he has ſo many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Volumes, and the Actions of ten thouſand times more Profeſſors to ſearch into, and make uſe of to his purpoſe: 'tis hard, if amongſt ſo many <hi>Writers</hi> and <hi>Livers</hi> there's no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for his turn. In this Channel has this Controverſie run hitherto, and ſo it may to the Worlds end: For, if all be <hi>True Repreſenting,</hi> that may be brought off by ſuch <hi>Shifts,</hi> as I have met with in the Courſe of this Debate, 'tis impoſſible there ſhould have been any <hi>Miſrepreſenters</hi> in the World ever ſince the Creation; unleſs it be ſuch who have only <hi>Malice</hi> enough to raiſe <hi>Calumnies,</hi> but want <hi>Wit</hi> to Gloſs upon the Report, and Colour the Deſign. Only ſuch as theſe are Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifi'd for the Character of <hi>Miſrepreſenting:</hi> for as for all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who have but ſo much of <hi>Eve</hi> in them, as to underſtand the Art of framing an <hi>Excuſe,</hi> they may boldly aſſert Falſities, raiſe groundleſs Jealouſies, miſconſtrue the Actions and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin of their Neighbors, extend Particulars to Univerſals, make what wreſted Inferences they pleaſe; yet 'tis <hi>True Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting</hi> all the while, as long as the Managers have but any thing to ſay in their own behalf, tho' it be nothing but to Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liate, and divert the Mind of the Reader: Such Returns as theſe made to the moſt <hi>Evident</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndeniable</hi> Charges of <hi>Miſrepreſenting,</hi> with the Title of An <hi>Anſwer</hi> in great Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters, and an <hi>Imprimatur</hi> to ſet it out, are Demonſtrations enough to the Crowd, to paſs Sentence upon the poor <hi>Papiſts</hi> for the worſt of Men, of whom they can hear or read nothing, but they are prepar'd beforehand to believe all, and pronounce them Guilty. And then let but a Man, who has a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of himſelf, come after all, and call it an <hi>Impudence</hi> in the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:65446:17"/> 
               <hi>Papiſts,</hi> not to make any <hi>Reply</hi> to <hi>ſuch Anſwers,</hi> which are only <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anſw. to Repr. Reflect. upon the State of Controv. p.</hi> 52.</note> too <hi>Impertinent</hi> to deſerve any, and then tell his Reader, that after all this Noiſe of <hi>Miſrepreſenting,</hi> the <hi>Papiſts</hi> have not been able to produce any <hi>one clear Inſtance</hi> to ſupport the Charge; the Point is clearly gain'd, and He that has but had Face enough to <hi>deny all,</hi> to make a few poor <hi>Shifts</hi> and <hi>Excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and call them <hi>Vindications,</hi> is brought off in Triumph, and nothing can be ſaid bad enough of the <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> who is now ſuppos'd to be left without a word to ſay for himſelf.</p>
            <p>For my part, I was always unwilling to employ my ſelf in ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in the <hi>Mire:</hi> 'twas enough once to point at it, I thought, without being oblig'd to rake in it as long as I liv'd. But it ſeems, now my Hand is once in, I muſt either chooſe to dwell there, or elſe be ſhouted at for deſerting the Poſt. Much good may it do thoſe, who long for ſo laſting an Entertainment in ſuch kind of Matter. However the Boaſts of a Noiſie Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary oblige me ſomething to croſs my Inclination; his cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouring Triumphs of the Cauſe being loſt, and that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not produce <hi>One clear Inſtance</hi> of our being <hi>Miſrepreſented,</hi> force me, upon the Public Score, to return to the making good the Charge. Having therefore here again recommended the Deciſion of this preſent Controverſie to the Obſervation of every ſincere and unbiaſs'd <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> deſiring them to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare ſuch <hi>Papiſts,</hi> as are of their <hi>Acquaintance,</hi> with the <hi>Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter</hi> of <hi>Papiſt,</hi> they have heard from the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> thereby to judge, whether we without reaſon complain; whether we are in reality <hi>Miſrepreſented</hi> or no. I'll once more enter upon that ungrateful Employment, of Examining ſome <hi>Proteſtant-True-Repreſenting Characters</hi> of <hi>Popery,</hi> to ſee how near they come to Truth; and whether it be poſſible to find <hi>One clear Inſtance</hi> to ſupport the Charge of our being <hi>Miſrepreſented.</hi> But becauſe there have been ſome Freſher and more Authentic Inſtances publiſh'd in a late Book Entitl'd <hi>Good Advice to the Pulpits,</hi> than thoſe I mention'd in my <hi>Laſt Reply,</hi> I'll rather chooſe to Examin ſome of Theſe, and conſider the Vindication that has been made of them, that ſo we may diſcover, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not only the <hi>Vulgar</hi> among <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are deceiv'd in their Notions of <hi>Popery;</hi> but likewiſe, what is of more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, whether thoſe, who are oblig'd by their <hi>Station</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:65446:17"/> and <hi>Character</hi> to be more Sincere, I mean their <hi>Guides,</hi> do not moſt evidently contribute to the imprinting theſe wrong No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the People, and upon ſuch falſe Grounds lay the Foundation of a great part of that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitableneſs, Animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity</hi> and <hi>Hatred,</hi> which too often they expreſs to Fellow-Chriſtians, more than becomes the <hi>True Profeſſors</hi> of the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of Peace.</hi> I proceed therefore to this Examen in the Method of the Book now mention'd: and firſt as to ſome Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Fact.</p>
            <div n="1" type="character">
               <head>Firſt Character of a Pulpit-Papiſt.</head>
               <argument>
                  <q>
                     <p>1. <hi>THE</hi> Papiſts <hi>in the Years</hi> 1679, 80, 81, <hi>were engag'd in a Horrid, Execrable and Helliſh Plot; they purſu'd it</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Good Advice.</note> 
                        <hi>on with Inſolence, Implacable Vigor and Malice.</hi> 2. <hi>The Prieſts abroad in Forreign Nations procur'd Money to carry on that Deviliſh Work.</hi> 3. <hi>Being Blood-thirſting Men, they then deſign'd to take away the Life of our late Sacred Majeſty.</hi> 4. <hi>They treacherouſly murder'd one of his Majeſty's</hi> Juſtices of the Peace, <hi>in cold Blood, with great Contrivance and Delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: hoping by his Death to ſtifle the Evidence that was brought againſt them, and prevent a farther Diſcovery. And they whom his Death doth not convince, neither will they be convinc'd, tho' he ſhould riſe again from the Dead.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </argument>
               <p>In theſe Colours were the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſet out by the <hi>Pulpits,</hi> in the Years above mention'd throughout the Nation, as <hi>Guilty of a moſt Helliſh and Execrable Deſign, as Thirſting the Blood of their Sovereign; As Barbarous Murderers; Engag'd in a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliſh Work; Men of Inſolence, Implacable Malice; A Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Vipers, Devils of Sedition and Faction, of Treaſon and Rebellion, Blood-thirſty and Deceitful Men,</hi> &amp;c. Now all this having been ſince prov'd <hi>Falſe,</hi> the <hi>Invention</hi> of <hi>Wicked Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians,</hi> and ſupported only by the <hi>Oaths</hi> of <hi>Perjur'd Men,</hi> the Queſtion is, Whether the <hi>Papiſts</hi> were not in all this time <hi>Miſrepreſented?</hi> And whether my <hi>Boaſting Adverſary</hi> has a Face to deny, that, after all our Complaint of being <hi>Miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented,</hi> we cannot produce <hi>One clear Inſtance</hi> to make good
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:65446:18"/> the Charge? Certainly, if to aſſert <hi>White</hi> Men to be <hi>Black,</hi> and to ſet out the <hi>Innocent</hi> as <hi>Guilty,</hi> and that of the moſt <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> of <hi>Crimes,</hi> be not <hi>Miſrepreſenting,</hi> there is then, I confeſs, no ſuch thing in the World.</p>
               <p>And yet however the <hi>Papiſts</hi> have been moſt barbarouſly us'd upon the ſuppos'd Guilt of theſe Crimes atteſted only by <hi>Profligate Wretches,</hi> and aſſerted by the <hi>Pulpits:</hi> Yet the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer</hi> in his <hi>Apology,</hi> pag. 5, 6. is ſo far from the <hi>Humility</hi> of doing the <hi>Papiſts</hi> Right in the Caſe, and compaſſionating them for the <hi>Cruelty,</hi> that by <hi>theſe Means</hi> was moſt unjuſtly drawn upon them, that he only minces the matter with his <hi>Iſs</hi> and his <hi>Ands;</hi> and being reſolv'd to ſay ſomething in favor of the <hi>Pulpits,</hi> he concludes, That if <hi>They err'd</hi> in Preaching thus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> they err'd with thoſe before whom they Preach'd, that is, with the greateſt Tribunal, and greateſt Part of the Nation. And what is this, but only by way of <hi>Defence,</hi> in ſome manner to acknowledge, that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> did not only wrongfully ſuffer in their Reputation from the <hi>Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits,</hi> but likewiſe in the Opinion of the greateſt Tribunal, and greateſt Part of the Nation. And this is the very thing I have all along pretended to prove. So that I hope now, after the Conviction of the <hi>Evidence</hi> of <hi>Perjury,</hi> and the <hi>Contradictions</hi> and <hi>Impoſſibilities</hi> of the <hi>Plot</hi> expos'd by a worthy Pen, we have <hi>One clear Inſtance</hi> at leaſt, of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> being <hi>Miſrepreſented.</hi> I am not for dwelling long upon this ungrateful Subject, only one thing I have to wonder at, and 'tis, That ſince the <hi>Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits</hi> had ſo great a ſhare in imprinting theſe <hi>Falſe</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt</hi> Notions in the People concerning the <hi>Papiſts;</hi> how it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens, that there is not one word heard from thoſe Places, in ſatisfaction of the Wrong that was done their Neighbor? Thoſe certainly, who pretend to teach others, ſhould not be backward in giving good Example: And eſpecially ſuch, who pretend to be clear from the Imputation of <hi>Miſrepreſenting,</hi> ought to do ſomething in this kind, and declare the <hi>Innocence</hi> of thoſe, whom they have help'd to proclaim <hi>Criminals.</hi> If they have <hi>err'd</hi> with thoſe, <hi>before whom</hi> they Preach'd, 'tis but reaſon with the ſame to revoke the Sentence they paſs'd, and reſtore the Reputation of thoſe, who ſuffer'd by their <hi>Error.</hi> The <hi>Judges</hi> and <hi>Bar</hi> have done this; The great Tribunal of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65446:18"/> 
                  <hi>Parliament</hi> too has not been wanting in Overtures of this kind; Only <hi>Tong</hi> died without Repentance, and <hi>Oats</hi> ſo lives: And excepting theſe, there are ſcarce any, that were concern'd in that <hi>Error,</hi> but what have moſt Chriſtian-like, made Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, beſides the Gentlemen of the <hi>Pulpits,</hi> who ſhould have been the firſt in leading the way. I can't tell how far <hi>theſe</hi> may think <hi>Satisfaction</hi> and open <hi>Repentance</hi> to be improper in their <hi>Station;</hi> but after ſo clear a Conviction of the <hi>Innocence</hi> of thoſe, whom they then <hi>accus'd,</hi> they muſt needs conclude it a <hi>Duty:</hi> and till they find a way to do it, one way or another, they muſt not take it amiſs, if as they were <hi>Miſrepreſenters</hi> then, they are eſteem'd <hi>Miſrepreſenters</hi> ſtill; ſince all that they aſſerted at that time in their Sermons, as to them, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains ſtill in full force, and with the Face of Truth, till it be openly revok'd, which was never done yet, as I can hear of.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="character">
               <head>Second Character of a Pulpit-Papiſt.</head>
               <argument>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>THE Popiſh Jeſuits had a Hand in that Horrid Plot of the</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Good Advice:</note> 
                        <hi>Murder of King</hi> Charles I. <hi>That Sacred and Royal Blood was not ſhed without the Concurrence and Aſſiſtance of the</hi> Papiſts. <hi>From</hi> Rome <hi>thoſe Dreadful Confuſions were highly fomented. The miſchievous and buſie Jeſuit promoted the Deſign, and was ſo Impudent as to boaſt of it. The Prieſt is well known, ſays one, who, when the Fatal Stroke was given, flouriſh'd with his Sword, and ſaid,</hi> Now the greateſt Enemy we have in the World is gone. <hi>The Church of</hi> Rome <hi>is juſtly accus'd of this Execrable Crime, and 'tis unjuſtly caſt on thoſe of the</hi> Reform'd Religion.</p>
                  </q>
               </argument>
               <p>This is another Character of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> extracted out of Sermons. 'Tis as Foul and Barbarous as well can be, and enough to make them odious in the ſight of good Chriſtians. If it be <hi>True,</hi> the <hi>Papiſts</hi> deſervedly ſuffer: but if <hi>Falſe,</hi> then certainly the <hi>Pulpits</hi> are <hi>Miſrepreſenters.</hi> And how far it is from Truth, I believe there are few, even of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> who know how to <hi>think</hi> without <hi>Paſſion,</hi> but have already conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. The <hi>Pulpits</hi> have a <hi>Groundleſs Story</hi> they produce, in behalf of what they aſſert; and we ſhew the contrary in an
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:65446:19"/> undeniable Teſtimony written in Characters of <hi>Blood</hi> of ſo many <hi>Noblemen, Gentry</hi> and <hi>Commonalty,</hi> who loſt their Lives in defence of that <hi>Prince,</hi> whom by the <hi>Pulpits</hi> they are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd to have <hi>Murder'd.</hi> Strange, that the <hi>Blood</hi> of ſo many <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſhould be ſpilt, and all under the <hi>Royal Standard,</hi> and yet <hi>They</hi> to be the <hi>Murderers,</hi> and their <hi>Church</hi> to be <hi>juſtly accus'd</hi> of that Execrable Crime! 'Tis well known that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ventur'd <hi>All</hi> in the Service of the <hi>Father:</hi> And the <hi>Challenge</hi> has been made to all ſorts of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> to produce even <hi>Ten Papiſts,</hi> I may ſay <hi>Two,</hi> that in all that Confuſion of Civil Wars, ever drew Sword againſt him. 'Tis as well known, that the Son our late Sovereign was ſhelter'd amongſt the <hi>Papiſts;</hi> that neither <hi>Promiſes</hi> nor <hi>Threats</hi> were powerful enough to move them from their Duty; and that even a <hi>Prieſt</hi> too, moſt Loyally hazarded his Life to ſave that of his Prince, by whoſe Care he was ſecur'd from the Fury of his Enemies, and preſerv'd for the Crown. This Evidence we have to atteſt the Loyalty of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> of thoſe Times, and yet the <hi>Pulpits</hi> ſtill declare, that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> had a Hand in the ſhedding of that <hi>Royal Blood.</hi> The <hi>Anſwerer</hi> has nothing to ſay here, but that we ought to conſult, <hi>not the Preachers,</hi> but the <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities</hi> they went upon. The Authority they have hitherto produc'd, is that of the <hi>French Preacher,</hi> which by ſober <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> themſelves, is reputed no better than a <hi>Fable.</hi> If thoſe that lay this Scandal upon <hi>Papiſts</hi> in their Sermons, think it to be otherwiſe, I wonder at leaſt, whether they can <hi>prove</hi> it to be ſo <hi>Great,</hi> as even to let this ſingle <hi>Authority</hi> by virtue of an <hi>Implicit Faith,</hi> weigh down thoſe other <hi>Teſtimonies</hi> of <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> viſible in the <hi>Blood</hi> of thoſe, who loſt their Lives in defence of their Sovereign. Till they do this, they only let <hi>weak Probability</hi> take place of <hi>Demonſtration,</hi> to the Defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming their Neighbor; and how far this falls ſhort of <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſenting,</hi> I leave the World to judge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="character">
               <head>Third Character of a Pulpit-Papiſt.</head>
               <argument>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>THE</hi> Papiſts, <hi>we are ſatisfied, were the Inſtruments in that</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Good Advice to Pulp. Caut.</hi> 2.</note> 
                        <hi>Judgment of the</hi> Fire of London, <hi>and caus'd</hi> London <hi>to</hi>
                        <pb n="17" facs="tcp:65446:19"/> 
                        <hi>fall juſt then when it was expected</hi> Rome <hi>ſhould; this was for the Advantage of their Cauſe: and we have too many Reaſons to think, they would pitch upon ſome ſuch Counſel: For ſuch things as theſe are now become their laſt Refuge, and the Arguments in which they expect moſt Succeſs. They find all Rational Attempts againſt us to be Fruitleſs: and therefore deſpairing of ever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing us like Men, they are reſolv'd to beat out our Brains (if they can) like Beaſts.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </argument>
               <p>This is a Character of <hi>Papiſts</hi> inſinuated into the Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Magiſtrates of the City of <hi>London,</hi> not in the time of that dreadful Fire, when that general Conſternation might have been a good Plea for an over credulous Accuſation; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Twenty years after, when the whole Matter had been throughly conſider'd. And tho' there were no other Grounds, whereon to build this Charge, beſides the <hi>Clamour</hi> and <hi>Affected Jealouſies</hi> of the <hi>People;</hi> and the Confeſſion of a Diſtracted Man, whoſe Religion was not much of any kind, but ſtill pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly <hi>Proteſtant.</hi> Yet upon theſe Grounds are the <hi>Papiſts</hi> repreſented, as the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> of that dreadful Judgment of the Fire of <hi>London,</hi> a Wickedneſs ſo Execrable, that 'tis not eaſily to be ſuppos'd the Crime of <hi>Men,</hi> but <hi>Fiends:</hi> Yet the <hi>Pulpits</hi> are <hi>ſatisfi'd</hi> that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> did it, for the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of their Cauſe. The People are perſuaded, that 'tis from ſuch <hi>Helliſh Means</hi> the <hi>Papiſts</hi> expect moſt <hi>Succeſs:</hi> and that becauſe they have nothing of <hi>Reaſon</hi> whereby to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail upon <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> rather than fail, they are reſolv'd to beat out their Brains like Beaſts. Strange Exaggerations from ſuch weak Grounds! And if this be not to paſs for <hi>Miſrepreſenting,</hi> they muſt have hard Foreheads, that muſt even pretend to diſcharge it from that ſo deſerv'd an Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. But however, to this are we forc'd by the Confidence of ſome Adverſaries, who after ſuch <hi>Raſh Aſſertions</hi> of theirs from the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> and the loading us with ſo much <hi>Infamy</hi> and <hi>Popular Hatred,</hi> upon ſuch <hi>light Preſumptions,</hi> are notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſo far from that <hi>Chriſtian Duty,</hi> of making the leaſt Satisfaction for this ſo conſiderable an Injury done both to our <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> that they even continue to imprint the <hi>Infamy</hi> yet deeper in the Hearts of the People, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:65446:20"/> the <hi>Complaints</hi> of our having been thus unjuſtly Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd, and pretending, that we cannot produce <hi>One clear In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> of our being <hi>Miſrepreſented.</hi> Is not this to vouch for the Truth of all that has been ever ſaid againſt us, and to affirm in one Breath, that, whether as to <hi>Oat's Plot,</hi> the <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Sir Edmondbury Godfrey,</hi> the <hi>Firing the City,</hi> and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever elſe of this kind, deliver'd out of the <hi>Pulpits,</hi> 'tis <hi>all True,</hi> the <hi>Papiſts are Guilty of all;</hi> and their <hi>Complaints of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miſrepreſented</hi> is but <hi>Vain</hi> and <hi>Idle.</hi> Are theſe <hi>Men,</hi> are they <hi>Preachers,</hi> can they be <hi>Chriſtians in earneſt,</hi> that thus play with the <hi>Reputation</hi> of their Neighbors in the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> blacken the greateſt part of the Chriſtian World, with the <hi>worſt of Crimes,</hi> upon ſuch <hi>poor Grounds,</hi> ſuch <hi>weak Evidence,</hi> and after the evident <hi>Falſity</hi> of ſome of theſe <hi>Charges,</hi> and the <hi>great Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probability</hi> of others, ſtill go on, and in ſome manner aſſert them over again in Print? I queſtion not, but they ſo far in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed get their Ends in all this, as to make us <hi>Contemptible</hi> and <hi>Odious;</hi> but I think the <hi>Actors</hi> and <hi>Promoters</hi> of ſuch <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Methods,</hi> are ſtill more Injurious to themſelves; and that whilſt they endeavor to defame the Religion of their Neighbors by <hi>Calumnies,</hi> they at the ſame time prove them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be no Chriſtians. Certainly theſe Men are to be pitied. And I wiſh they would conſider, that if their Liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood comes in by <hi>Preaching or Writing Controverſie,</hi> there are many other <hi>Honeſt Ways</hi> of getting a Livelihood, and no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of taking this. There's a late Adverſary of mine, who has had ſome ſerious thoughts upon this Subject, and being convinc'd, I ſuppoſe, of the Unchriſtian Effects of ſuch Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, he makes this free Declaration for himſelf in theſe words: <q>I will here take occaſion to ſay a good word of <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anſw. to Repr. Reſtect. upon the State of the Controv. p.</hi> 27.</note> my ſelf, and that is, That rather than prevaricate in things of this nature, I would make very hard Shifts: If it were too late to apply my ſelf to Handicraft Trades, yet, may be, I could <hi>Dig,</hi> or the like: But if I could not <hi>Dig,</hi> I would not be aſham'd to <hi>Beg.</hi> Perhaps I might get ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by turning my Pen another way, and writing of things where I had more liberty; as by writing <hi>Almanacks,</hi> or any ſuch thing, where Miſtakes will be committed in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, and are forgiven in courſe, and will be ſure to do no
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:65446:20"/> body any hurt: but to impoſe upon Men in Books that treat of Divinity, or to accuſe Men (from the Pulpit, he ſhould have added) of the greateſt Villanies upon vain Reports, weak Preſumptions, or light Probabilities, is one of the laſt Diſhoneſt things I would take to: I ſhould think of that, and taking a convenient Stand near the Town, much about the ſame time; and the reaſon why he that do's the one, do's not the other, is becauſe all Mens Abilities do not lie the ſame way.</q> Thus this Good Man Meditates and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves with himſelf; 'tis pity he had not thought of this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: for certainly, he's ſo far in the right, that <hi>Digging, Begging,</hi> or making <hi>Almanacks,</hi> are much more <hi>Innocent</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, than <hi>Deluding of Souls;</hi> and however <hi>Murthering</hi> Men in their <hi>Reputation</hi> has been ſo <hi>Divine</hi> a thing of late Years, yet certainly thoſe, who have their convenient Stands near the Town, are not concern'd in ſo <hi>Extenſive</hi> a Miſchief. And I don't queſtion, but thoſe Few, who have ſeriouſly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd the <hi>weight</hi> of this <hi>Crime,</hi> and the <hi>blackneſs</hi> of the <hi>Guilt,</hi> are ſo far from going on in that kind of <hi>Divinity,</hi> that they could wiſh all that Pains ſo employ'd, had been ſpent in <hi>Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging</hi> or <hi>Begging,</hi> or making of <hi>Almanacks,</hi> tho' this, it may be, had never turn'd to ſo good an Account. However, Mending is never out of Seaſon, and I cannot but commend theſe good Reſolutions, tho' late, of our good Friend, who, by his requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring nothing more than a <hi>Good Example</hi> to follow, I perceive, is ſufficiently ſenſible of his <hi>Guilt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="character">
               <head>Fourth Character of a Pulpit-Papiſt.</head>
               <argument>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>THE</hi> Papiſts <hi>have their Emiſſaries up and down to</hi> Preach <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Good Advice to Pulp. Caut.</hi> 5.</note> Schiſm <hi>and</hi> Sedition <hi>into Peoples Ears. By ſuch Arts as theſe they inſinuate themſelves among the poor deluded People of our</hi> Separate Congregations, <hi>and joyning with them in their Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours againſt the Church of</hi> England, <hi>crying it down for</hi> Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious <hi>and</hi> Popiſhly affected, <hi>they paſs for Gifted Brethren, and real</hi> Popery <hi>is carry'd on by ſuch Diſguiſes.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </argument>
               <p>Here again the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are ſet forth in a <hi>Sermon</hi> before the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65446:21"/> Honorable Judges, as great <hi>Hypocrites, Religious Cheats,</hi> and <hi>Impoſtors,</hi> Qualities black enough to make them Odious and Deteſtable. For certainly, tho' <hi>Diſſimulation</hi> and <hi>Deluſion</hi> be abominable every where, yet never more, than in Spiritual Matters, and Concerns of the Soul: there being no Impiety poſſibly greater, than that of Preaching <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Sedition,</hi> under the Cloak of <hi>Sanctity</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> and thus, in <hi>Sheeps</hi> Clothing, to play the <hi>Wolves.</hi> Yet this is, from the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> made to be the Character of <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and the <hi>Judges</hi> are perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> under the Diſguiſe of <hi>Diſſenting Teachers,</hi> Preach to the Separate Congregations; and by this Impoſture put them upon the greateſt of Evils both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State.</hi> A Foul Crime! and if <hi>True,</hi> ſufficient to caſt the <hi>Papiſts</hi> out of the number of <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> but if <hi>Falſe,</hi> and not as is here ſet out, as ſufficient on the other ſide, to bring the <hi>Pulpits</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that as black Character of <hi>Miſrepreſenting.</hi> This Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation was ſet down in the <hi>Advice to the Pulpits,</hi> and all the Return that is made to it in the Anſwer, is, as above, That <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Anſw. to Good Advice, p.</hi> 7.</note> we muſt <hi>conſult the Authorities the Preachers went upon in urging this Charge againſt the Papiſts.</hi> Now who would not have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, that any <hi>Anſwerer,</hi> zealous in acquitting the <hi>Pulpits,</hi> would have not only produc'd the <hi>Authorities,</hi> but likewiſe have ſpent a few Lines in making good ſuch <hi>Authorities,</hi> and proving them to be <hi>Authentic</hi> beyond exception? The <hi>Pulpits</hi> muſt needs be ſenſible, that the <hi>Crime</hi> laid to the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> is of the blackeſt Dye; and that Men who pretend to Conſcience, and to <hi>Reforming</hi> Conſciences too, ought not to ſpread <hi>Reports</hi> of their <hi>Neighbor,</hi> in a Matter of the <hi>higheſt Scandal,</hi> but upon <hi>ſubſtantial Grounds,</hi> and an <hi>Evidence</hi> of the <hi>Guilt;</hi> and that 'tis the Concern of their Reputation thus to make good all their Proceedings in this kind. This an <hi>Apologizer for the Pulpits</hi> ſhould have done: But inſtead of this, he ſends us to conſult the <hi>Quaker <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmaſk'd,</hi> the <hi>New Diſcovery,</hi> and in want of theſe, a Book call'd <hi>Foxes and Firebrands:</hi> He might likewiſe have added the <hi>Preface</hi> to Dr. <hi>Teniſon</hi>'s late Account of a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with <hi>A. P.</hi> for as far as I can learn, the <hi>Quaker <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſk'd, Foxes and Firebrands,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Teniſon</hi>'s <hi>Gubbards,</hi> are much of a Piece. Good God! that Men ſhould pretend to teach their Auditory the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and expound to them the Truth of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:65446:21"/> 
                  <hi>God's Word,</hi> and when They are thus Challeng'd in a Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of this moment, then to fly to <hi>Foxes</hi> and <hi>Firebrands,</hi> and lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the <hi>Scripture,</hi> take refuge in <hi>Libels,</hi> and <hi>Street-Pamphlets!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is a moſt ſurpriſing way of making <hi>Apologies for the Pulpits,</hi> of ſuch <hi>Pulpits</hi> too, from whence there has been ſo many fierce Declamations made, againſt reading of <hi>Legends,</hi> believing the <hi>Inventions of Men,</hi> and truſting to <hi>Idle Stories,</hi> the Dreams of Melancholy Recluſes. Upon theſe Topics are the <hi>Papiſts</hi> run down by the <hi>Pulpits,</hi> derided and expos'd as Men of a <hi>light Faith,</hi> who exchange the <hi>Scripture</hi> for theſe em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pty <hi>Fables.</hi> And when a <hi>Preacher</hi> is warm upon this Subject, then out come the Miracles of the <hi>Great Xaverius,</hi> the Wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Life of St. <hi>Mary Magdalen de Pazzi,</hi> the <hi>Revelations</hi> of St. <hi>Bridget,</hi> &amp;c. And theſe are made uſe of to ſhew, what un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely Stories the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſwallow, and upon what falſe Grounds they build their Belief. Now, who would not believe, that Thoſe, who make theſe <hi>Invectives,</hi> ſhould be careful in <hi>avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> what they pretend to <hi>Reform;</hi> and be ſure not to out-doe the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> in the very thing they condemn them? And yet ſee their Fate. Whilſt they are drawing out the <hi>Character</hi> of <hi>Papiſts</hi> in theſe Colours, they e'en make a moſt exact Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of themſelves; and <hi>Proteſtant Preachers</hi> are no ſooner Challeng'd in their <hi>Pulpit-Narratives,</hi> but we are bid conſult the <hi>Authorities</hi> they went upon; and what <hi>Authorities</hi> are theſe? We are ſent to the <hi>Quaker <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmaſk'd,</hi> to the <hi>New Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery,</hi> to <hi>Foxes and Firebrands:</hi> And theſe are ſtil'd the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities they go upon.</hi> As if theſe were more <hi>Authentic</hi> than the <hi>Miracles</hi> of S. <hi>Xaverius,</hi> which have been ſo ſtrictly Examin'd, that even ſome <hi>pretended Reformers</hi> themſelves have judg'd them worthy of Credit. And here, while I am upon this Subject, I cannot but admire ſome <hi>Proteſtant Preachers, Writers,</hi> and other otherwiſe ſober <hi>Laymen</hi> of late, who take upon them thus to Ridicule, and ſlightingly to wonder at the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> for this their <hi>Fond Credulity</hi> forſooth, in relation to <hi>Old Legends,</hi> and <hi>Modern Lives of Saints:</hi> Whenas, if theſe ſame <hi>Preachers</hi> and <hi>Lay-men</hi> do but look a little back over their own Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, they cannot but ſee yet in ſight, ſuch a Heap of <hi>Monſtrous Legends,</hi> I mean the <hi>Perjuries</hi> and <hi>Contradictory Fables</hi> of <hi>Oats</hi> and <hi>Tong,</hi> &amp;c. ſolemnly Preach'd up in <hi>Pulpits,</hi> by the moſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:65446:22"/> Eminent Men of the Nation, and as eagerly ſwallow'd by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finit numbers of the People, that they cannot without Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion cenſure the <hi>Credulity</hi> of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> whilſt they conſider how deeply they themſelves have given ſuch Credit to <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibilities.</hi> And this is very obſervable in the way, that there is ſcarce any thing in all thoſe Books objected upon this ſcore againſt the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> whether <hi>Ancient</hi> or <hi>Modern Legends,</hi> but however incredible it may appear, yet generally is all in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to a good End, and to the working Chriſtian Effects in the Reader; ſcarce a Miracle related, but raiſes the Admiration of God's <hi>Power,</hi> his <hi>Goodneſs</hi> and <hi>Mercy;</hi> ſcarce a Paſſage, but is a Recommendation of ſome <hi>Vertue,</hi> an Encouragement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Vice,</hi> &amp;c. and cannot be read without a great Spiritual Advantage to every unprejudic'd Chriſtian. In ſuch things as theſe it is the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are condemn'd for <hi>over-credulous;</hi> tho' even as to all theſe too, the <hi>Church</hi> lays no Obligation on any, of Aſſenting or Subſcribing to the <hi>Truth</hi> of them; but allows them to be read, as it do's other Hiſtory, to which every one gives credit, in proportion to the <hi>Authority</hi> which they find for what is related. But whilſt the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach'd, for being of <hi>too haſty</hi> a Belief in things of <hi>this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> ſee which way the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> lean: They are taught not to be <hi>too Credulous</hi> in things relating to <hi>God,</hi> to the Works of his <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> &amp;c. No; here they are bid be <hi>Cautious,</hi> to be <hi>Prudent,</hi> not to <hi>Truſt</hi> to others; but be ſure keep cloſe to their own <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and not to <hi>believe Raſhly</hi> or <hi>Blindly.</hi> But then, let them but turn on the other ſide, and let the Matter be nothing of <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Heaven;</hi> but <hi>againſt Popery</hi> and the <hi>Papiſts;</hi> here They <hi>believe</hi> without <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint:</hi> there's no <hi>Miracle</hi> too great, no <hi>Extravagancy</hi> ſo <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable,</hi> no <hi>Legend</hi> ſo full of <hi>Contradictions,</hi> but 'tis receiv'd without ſcruple, and as greedily ſwallow'd, as eaſily believ'd; and the very <hi>Pulpits</hi> too, that know how to cry down the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> for an <hi>over-credulity</hi> in Matters of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Devotion,</hi> ſhall now in Matters of <hi>Defamation,</hi> of <hi>Malice,</hi> of <hi>Intereſt,</hi> tending to the Ruin of their Neighbor, tell how to be as <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous</hi> as any. And tho' they condemn the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> for appealing to <hi>Councils,</hi> the Relations of Holy Fathers, and the Examination of Commiſſioners, in taking up Miracles upon their Credit; yet
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:65446:22"/> when they themſelves are put in mind of the <hi>Improbable</hi> and <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible</hi> Stories, they have help'd to ſpread from their <hi>Pulpits,</hi> they without Bluſhing fly to the Authority of <hi>Foxes and Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands, Proclamations</hi> and <hi>Votes</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> as if theſe were more <hi>Infallible</hi> than thoſe others; and as if the Preaching and Believing <hi>Legends</hi> of <hi>Malice</hi> and <hi>Envy,</hi> were Marks of a <hi>True Chriſtian;</hi> when to receive <hi>Miracles</hi> in order to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of <hi>Piety</hi> and a <hi>Good Life,</hi> are made to be ſo <hi>Ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtian.</hi> I muſt beg the Reader's Pardon for this little Digreſſion; 'tis a Subject of which the <hi>Pulpit</hi> often rings, and is as often objected by <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Writers, and ſo not unworthy of a ſhort Remark for the ſhewing the Perverſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their way of Reaſoning: and eſpecially too, becauſe I ſhall have an occaſion of referring to it afterwards, before the cloſe of this Diſcourſe</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="character">
               <head>Fifth Character of a Pulpit-Papiſt.</head>
               <argument>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>THE different</hi> Orders <hi>of Religion amongſt the</hi> Papiſts, <hi>are</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Good Advice to Pulp. Caut.</hi> 3.</note> 
                        <hi>neither better nor worſe than ſo many</hi> Sects, <hi>and ſeveral Caſts of Religion; only they have that advantage in managing their</hi> Diviſions, <hi>which we have not; to pack up their</hi> Fanatics <hi>in Convents and Cloyſters, and ſo bring them under ſome kind of Rule and Government.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </argument>
               <p>Thus were the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſet out in a Sermon at <hi>Whitehall</hi> in the Year 1675. in which the <hi>Preacher</hi> being deſirous to take off that Foul Blemiſh of ſo many <hi>Sects</hi> and <hi>Diviſions</hi> rending the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Church of <hi>England,</hi> inconſiſtent with the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s True Church, and ſo often objected againſt them by <hi>Catholics,</hi> falls into that common Topic of covering the Defects of his own Church by Calumniating that of his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor: and therefore he boldly makes up to his Auditory, and tells them, That the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity the Papiſts boaſt of in their Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, is but a Pretence; whereas,</hi> ſays he, <hi>They have readly more Diviſions in their Religion, than they charge ours with;</hi> and then goes on in the words of the <hi>Character</hi> above cited: In which he Repreſents the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> 1. To be divided into
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:65446:23"/> 
                  <hi>many Sects,</hi> and <hi>different Caſts of Religion.</hi> 2. That the <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Orders</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> are neither better nor worſe, than ſo many <hi>Sects.</hi> And that the only Advantage of that Church above <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> is, that they pack up their <hi>Fanatics</hi> into <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents,</hi> ſo to bring them under Government. Now what <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant</hi> was there in his Auditory, or what ſuch <hi>Reader</hi> of his Sermon, reflecting what the <hi>Sects</hi> and <hi>different Caſts of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> and what the ſo call'd <hi>Fanaticks</hi> are here in <hi>England,</hi> but would preſently receive this Notion imprinted as a <hi>Truth</hi> in his Head; that as in in <hi>England,</hi> ſo likewiſe in the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> are there <hi>different Sects</hi> of Religion, and <hi>Fanatics</hi> to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide it, but only that there they are ſhut up in <hi>Convents</hi> for better Order? This is what the Preacher plainly and poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively aſſerts, and whoſoever takes him at his word, muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily believe ſo. But becauſe this is nothing better nor worſe, than an <hi>Abſolute Falſhood,</hi> 'twas therefore ſet down in the <hi>Advice to the Pulpits</hi> as an unjuſt <hi>Character,</hi> and a <hi>Miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation</hi> of the <hi>Papiſts;</hi> and Caution given of it upon that ſcore, as a thing to be avoided by all Honeſt, Sincere, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Preachers, who deſire to ſpeak nothing of themſelves, nor againſt their Neighbors, but the down-right Truth.</p>
               <p>However the <hi>Apologizer</hi> for the <hi>Pulpits</hi> in his <hi>Anſwer, pag.</hi> 11. being reſolv'd to Vindicate, and bring off all that has been ſaid in thoſe Chairs, as if never any thing had been <hi>raſhly</hi> bolted out there, comes with a <hi>Let us try what ground the Preacher had for ſuch Aſſertions:</hi> And then as to that where the <hi>Preacher</hi> ſays, <hi>Their Orders among the Papiſts are ſo many Sects;</hi> that is, ſays the <hi>Anſwerer, So many diſtinct Bodies, that having different Founders, Rules, Habits, and often Opinions, by which an Emulation is begot betwixt Order and Order, they become divided among themſelves.</hi> Would not a School-boy have been Scourg'd for ſuch a ſleeveleſs, frivolous Excuſe? The Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, without mincing it, ſays, That the <hi>different Orders of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion amongſt the Papiſts, are neither better nor worſe than ſo many Sects;</hi> that is, ſays the Apologizer, <hi>So many diſtinct Bodies,</hi> &amp;c. How low are we fall'n below the <hi>Pulpit-Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter!</hi> As if <hi>Diviſions</hi> in Religion, and <hi>different Sects,</hi> were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but ſo <hi>many diſtinct Bodies, having different Founders, Rules,</hi> &amp;c. If a Preacher of the <hi>Catholic</hi> Communion ſhould in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:65446:23"/> the like terms poſitively declare in a Sermon, That the <hi>Two <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities,</hi> and every <hi>Colledge</hi> in them, wherein are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally Educated and fitted for the <hi>Pulpit</hi> all the <hi>Parſons</hi> in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> are neither better nor worſe than the Seminaries of ſo <hi>many different Sects and ſeveral Caſts of Religion,</hi> and the <hi>Fellows</hi> are ſo many <hi>Fanatics</hi> pack'd up in an Encloſure under Rule; I don't queſtion but the Town would ſoon be fill'd with the News of ſuch an Impoſtor, for being ſo Impudent in infuſing ſuch Falſe Notions into his Hearers. And would not he have an Excellent Apologizer to help him out, if another to vindicate the Paſſage, ſhould Print in his behalf, &amp; ſay, That by the <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Two <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities being ſo many Sects and different Caſts of Religion,</hi> the Preacher only meant, <hi>So many diſtinct Bodies, that having different Founders, Rules, Habits, and often Opinions, by which an Emulation is begot betwixt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity, Colledge and Colledge, they become divided among themſelves, and when occaſion is offer'd, do actually war one upon another in their way?</hi> What would the World ſay of ſuch Doings as theſe, but only condemn the <hi>Preacher</hi> for raſhly aſperſing ſuch Bodies of Men, and the <hi>Vindicator</hi> for a <hi>vain Trifler,</hi> in publiſhing ſuch an Idle Apology? And yet this is our Caſe, it being well known to any one, that has but a grain more of Truth than what he has learn'd from the <hi>Pulpits,</hi> that thoſe <hi>ſeveral Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Orders</hi> amongſt <hi>Catholics,</hi> notwithſtanding their <hi>different Founders, Rules, Habits, School-Opinions,</hi> and <hi>Emulation,</hi> do live as entirely within the <hi>Communion</hi> of the <hi>ſame Church,</hi> embrace and teach all the <hi>ſame Articles of Faith,</hi> ſay the ſame <hi>Creed, Preach, Pray,</hi> and Adminiſter the <hi>Sacraments</hi> in one anothers <hi>Churches,</hi> and are every way in as perfect a Union as the <hi>Two <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities,</hi> which with their <hi>different Founders, Rules, Habits, School-Opinions,</hi> and <hi>Emulation,</hi> are yet Members of the ſame Communion, and ſubject to the ſame Church of <hi>England.</hi> And then let the World judge, what a great Truth that was of this <hi>Preacher,</hi> aſſerting <hi>Theſe</hi> to be ſo many <hi>Sects and different Caſts of Religion.</hi> Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> could have told him, That <hi>Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tics</hi> (or Sectaries) <hi>in the Church, are juſt as Rebels in a Kingdom, not as part of it, but as open and profeſs'd Enemies:</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, that the <hi>different Corporations</hi> and <hi>Bodies</hi> of Men here in <hi>London,</hi> under different <hi>Founders, Rules</hi> and <hi>Practices,</hi> might,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:65446:24"/> with the ſame colour of Reaſon, be Preach'd up for ſo many <hi>Rebels,</hi> as the <hi>Religious Orders</hi> for <hi>ſo many Sects;</hi> whilſt <hi>Theſe</hi> are only ſo many <hi>different Parts</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> as <hi>Thoſe</hi> are of the <hi>Kingdom.</hi> But now for the <hi>Fanatics in Convents.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Preacher</hi> declar'd, that in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> they have <hi>Fanatics</hi> too; but they take care to <hi>ſhut them up in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents.</hi> By what is already ſaid, the Reader may perceive, that ſuch as are in <hi>Convents</hi> in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> are Men, who embracing a Retir'd Life, dedicate themſelves to the Service of God, in Praying, Faſting, Mortification, and the other Exerciſes of a Pious Chriſtian, ſome according to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of S. <hi>Benedict,</hi> others of S. <hi>Francis,</hi> others of S. <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minic,</hi> &amp;c. which however different in the <hi>Practice</hi> of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Life, yet are all in perfect Obedience to the <hi>ſame Church-Authority,</hi> and of the <hi>ſame Belief;</hi> as may be ſeen here in <hi>England,</hi> where there are Monks of S. <hi>Benedict</hi>'s Order, <hi>Friers</hi> of S. <hi>Francis,</hi> &amp;c. and yet Theſe are ſo far from making any <hi>Diviſions</hi> in the Church, of which they are <hi>Members,</hi> that they all acknowledge one and the ſame, as their <hi>Common Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and are only as different <hi>Parts,</hi> not <hi>dividing,</hi> but <hi>making up</hi> the <hi>Whole.</hi> This may be ſeen in Queen Dowager's Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel at <hi>Somerſet-houſe,</hi> in which Officiate <hi>Monks, Friars, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicans, Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Clergy,</hi> that is, ſo many <hi>different Orders</hi> of Men, and yet without any difference in Religion, or diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement in Faith. Now how unlike is this, to what the <hi>Preacher</hi> delivers! How different are Theſe, from what is <hi>commonly</hi> here underſtood, and the Church of <hi>England</hi> calls <hi>Fanatics?</hi> But however the <hi>Apologizer</hi> is to bring him off? And therefore <hi>Fanaticiſm,</hi> ſays he, <hi>is a general Name, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends in it Superſtition and Enthuſiaſm.</hi> So that <hi>Religious Men</hi> in <hi>Convents</hi> are <hi>Fanatics</hi> forſooth, becauſe they are <hi>acted by ſome ſuppos'd Revelations, Viſions, Raptures, and unaccountable Impulſes.</hi> What Controverſial Stuff is this! Why, at this rate he might make <hi>Fanatics</hi> of all the <hi>Patriarchs</hi> and <hi>Prophets,</hi> of S. <hi>Joſeph,</hi> S. <hi>Peter</hi> and S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> and moſt of all of S. <hi>John,</hi> whoſe whole Book of <hi>Revelations</hi> is nothing now, it ſeems, but ſo much <hi>Fanaticiſm;</hi> Marry, well-fare ſuch <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natics:</hi> I wiſh the <hi>Church-of-England-men</hi> were ſuch <hi>Fanatics</hi> too; and were acted a little more by ſuch <hi>Viſions, Revelations</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:65446:24"/> and <hi>Divine Impulſes,</hi> inſtead of thoſe we have ſeen of late Years, when the <hi>Viſions</hi> of Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfrey,</hi> and the Suggeſtions of <hi>Parſon Tong</hi> and <hi>Oats,</hi> with ſome other <hi>Helps</hi> not altogether <hi>Divine,</hi> mov'd the <hi>Pulpits</hi> as <hi>ſtrongly</hi> and <hi>Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically,</hi> as if all had come directly from Heaven. But ſee now whither we are driven by the Conduct of a cloſe <hi>Vindicator.</hi> The <hi>Preacher</hi> told his Auditory, 1. That in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> there are <hi>really</hi> more <hi>Diviſions,</hi> than they charge <hi>Ours</hi> with. 2. That their <hi>Religious Orders</hi> are neither better nor worſe, than ſo <hi>many Sects,</hi> and <hi>ſeveral Caſts of Religion.</hi> 3. That they have their <hi>Fanatics</hi> pack'd up in <hi>Convents.</hi> And now upon the management of the whole Matter by the <hi>Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator,</hi> 'tis all ſunk into this: That the <hi>Religious Orders are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Bodies, having different Founders, Rules,</hi> &amp;c. And that in their <hi>Convents, ſome are acted by ſuppoſed Illuminations, Raptures, and unaccountable Impulſes.</hi> Who could ever have fall'n into this Account, without the aſſiſtance of ſuch an Expounder! And do's he think in earneſt, that the Auditory underſtood it, as he has now laid it out? He knows they are not us'd to ſuch favourable Conſtructions in things relating to the <hi>Papiſts;</hi> they may make things worſe indeed, but ſeldom, I fear, take off from any thing they hear thus poſitively aſſerted in the <hi>Pulpit.</hi> And therefore, conſidering how different this Notion is from what thoſe Words of the <hi>Preacher,</hi> according to the <hi>general</hi> and <hi>vulgar</hi> acceptance, do import, he muſt give me leave to ſet down thoſe <hi>Three Aſſertions</hi> of the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> for ſo many <hi>Clear Inſtances</hi> of moſt <hi>Foul Miſrepreſenting.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="character">
               <head>Sixth Character of a Pulpit-Papiſt.</head>
               <argument>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IN the</hi> Roman <hi>Church it</hi> (the Sacrament) <hi>muſt</hi> now <hi>be no longer a Repreſentative, but a Real, Propitiatory Sacrifice;</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> 
                        <hi>and Chriſt's Natural Body</hi> muſt be <hi>brought down from Heaven upon a Thouſand Altars at once, and there really broken,—and his Blood actually ſpilt a Thouſand times every Day.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </argument>
               <p>Thus is this Doctrin of <hi>Catholics</hi> render'd in a Sermon at <hi>Oxford</hi> 1679. and in theſe few words are Two things Falſly
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:65446:25"/> ſhewn, 1. The <hi>Sacrifice of the Altar</hi> is made to be <hi>no longer a Repreſentative Sacrifice:</hi> whereas <hi>Catholics</hi> believe, that <hi>it is Repreſentative.</hi> 2. That <hi>Chriſt's Body is really broken, and his Blood actually ſpilt upon the Altar:</hi> whereas <hi>Catholics are taught,</hi> that this is done <hi>only Sacramentally</hi> or <hi>Myſtically.</hi> And what's the Plea of the <hi>Apologizer?</hi> Only, that this is not <hi>poſitively aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted</hi> of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> Doctrin, but only a <hi>Natural Inference,</hi> and an Arguing againſt them upon their own Principles. And this is apparent, becauſe, ſays he, the words <hi>Now</hi> and <hi>Muſt be,</hi> ſhew what the <hi>Preacher</hi> meant. To ſuch a nice Point is the <hi>Vindicator</hi> reduc'd, to bring off the <hi>Preacher:</hi> ſo that to all ſuch as, at that Sermon, did not underſtand the virtue of that <hi>Now</hi> and <hi>Muſt be,</hi> there are theſe <hi>Two Falſities</hi> ſuggeſted of the <hi>Papiſts:</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant awkward Reaſoning</hi> is ſet out for <hi>True Catholic Doctrin:</hi> which is as bad <hi>Miſrepreſenting</hi> as can be. 'Tis not my Province here to examin the Truth of ſuch <hi>Reaſoning</hi> and <hi>Inferences:</hi> but yet, I fancy, there are few Men of Senſe, who don't ſee throughly the weakneſs of ſuch <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions;</hi> whilſt 'tis ſo eaſily reconcileable with Reaſon and Scripture, and ſo intelligible, that <hi>Chriſt really Preſent in the Sacrament</hi> may be offer'd to God upon the Altar by the Hands of the Prieſt, in <hi>Remembrance</hi> of the ſame Chriſt offering him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Victim upon the <hi>Croſs</hi> for the Redemption of Man: and conſequently, that the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of the <hi>Altar</hi> is <hi>Repreſentative</hi> of that upon the <hi>Croſs.</hi> Mr. <hi>Thorndike</hi> never ſcrupled the leaſt <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epil. to Trag. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 11.</note> at this, expreſly owning the <hi>Elements chang'd into the Body and Blood of Chriſt, to be truly the Sacrifice of Chriſt upon the Croſs,</hi> and to be <hi>both Propitiatory</hi> and <hi>Impetratory;</hi> and yet never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd it to be perform'd likewiſe in <hi>Remembrance of Chriſt Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified.</hi> The other is not more difficult to be conceiv'd, <hi>viz.</hi> How <hi>Chriſt's Body</hi> may be <hi>Really preſent</hi> in this <hi>Sacrament,</hi> and yet his <hi>Body</hi> not <hi>Really broken</hi> there, nor his <hi>Blood actually ſpilt:</hi> ſince 'tis not Preſent there <hi>Corporeally,</hi> but <hi>Sacramentally</hi> only; which <hi>manner of Preſence</hi> is no more conſiſtent with <hi>real Break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> or <hi>Spilling,</hi> than are <hi>Spirits,</hi> or the <hi>Glorified Bodies</hi> of the Bleſſed, which tho' <hi>real</hi> and <hi>ſubſtantial Bodies</hi> ſtill, are not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding not at all ſuſceptible of thoſe <hi>Corporeal Accidents.</hi> But however this may be obvious to any unbiaſs'd Judgment; yet we are, it ſeems, to be expos'd, according to every Man's
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:65446:25"/> Perverſe Notions; and every <hi>little-half-pac'd Divine</hi> is to ſet us out under all the <hi>Groſſeſt Abſurdities,</hi> which he pretends are in our Doctrin, but are really nothing, but the rough thoughts of his own Inventive Brain: and if this be to paſs for <hi>True Repreſenting</hi> in a <hi>Pulpit,</hi> God defend all good Chriſtians from the Edifications of ſuch Truths.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="character">
               <head>Seventh Character of a Pulpit-Papiſt.</head>
               <argument>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>POpery puts out the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings of thoſe of her own Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Good Advice to Pulp. Caut.</hi> 3.</note> 
                        <hi>and tears out the Hearts of all others: whom ſhe cannot deceive, ſhe will deſtroy. The Abſurdity of</hi> Auricular Confeſſion <hi>is endleſs, where a Man unlades himſelf of all his Sins, by whiſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them into Prieſts Ears. Likewiſe</hi> Tranſubſtantiation, <hi>where Men muſt renounce all their Five Senſes. The Pope's</hi> Infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity <hi>keeps a good decorum with the reſt. He alone cannot err, and all others, without ſome of his aſſiſtance, cannot but err.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </argument>
               <p>After this manner was <hi>Popery</hi> deſcrib'd in a Preface to a Sermon at <hi>Guild-hall</hi> 1679. and ſo much to a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that were it ſuch a Religion, as is in theſe few Lines de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd, 'twere nothing leſs than the Duty of every Reaſonable Chriſtian to <hi>proteſt</hi> againſt it. But as long as theſe <hi>Deformities</hi> are only the Contrivances of her. Diſingenuous Character-making Adverſaries, they only ſerve as an Argument to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm her Profeſſors in their Religion, whilſt they behold it Attaqued only by the Unchriſtian Artifices of <hi>Paſſion</hi> and <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſture.</hi> And let the Reader ſee how much theſe are concern'd in this Character, in which there are as many <hi>Calumnies</hi> as <hi>Lines.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. It aſſerts, That <hi>Popery puts out the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding of thoſe of her own Communion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is falſe; ſince 'tis certain, that <hi>Catholics</hi> have the ſame li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of uſing and improving their Underſtanding, as the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of any other Chriſtian Society in the World; and there are none of her <hi>Deſerters</hi> whatſoever, that have half ſo many <hi>Books, Catechiſms, Commentaries, Expoſitions,</hi> &amp;c. for Inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Members in all the <hi>Myſteries</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Practical.</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:65446:26"/> Duties of a Chriſtian, as <hi>They;</hi> and if this be <hi>putting out the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings of thoſe of her own Communion,</hi> whilſt it takes ſo much care for the making them underſtand their Religion; then certainly thoſe that help Men <hi>to ſee better,</hi> may be as truly ſaid, <hi>to put out their Eyes.</hi> There's none certainly but knows, that whoſoever will be a Chriſtian, muſt <hi>ſubmit his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> to the Belief of ſuch <hi>Myſteries</hi> as are <hi>above it;</hi> this <hi>Catholics</hi> are taught to do: and <hi>Proteſtants</hi> too, if they have Chriſtian <hi>Faith,</hi> muſt do the like. S. <hi>Paul</hi> read this Leſſon long ago to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 2 <hi>Ep.</hi> 10. 5. where he teaches them to <hi>Bring into captivity every Thought to the Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Chriſt.</hi> This <hi>captivity of our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding to Chriſt,</hi> and to the <hi>Myſteries</hi> he taught, is an <hi>improving,</hi> and <hi>illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating</hi> the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> and <hi>no putting of it out.</hi> And if it be upon this ſcore, he lays this Scandal upon us, let him but take a <hi>Jew</hi> along with him, and, upon the ſame ground, he'll ſee as much done for S. <hi>Paul.</hi> 'Tis our comfort ſtill, that in all things touching <hi>Faith,</hi> we have <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his <hi>Catholic Church</hi> to direct us: while we ſubmit to this, we go ſafe and Rationally, and being taught to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand all thus propos'd to the beſt of our Capacity, there's no danger of our <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding being put out.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Popery tears out the Hearts of all others</hi> (out of her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion;) <hi>whom ſhe cannot deceive, ſhe will deſtroy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is falſe too, ſince tho' <hi>Catholics</hi> are bid to go and <hi>Teach all Nations,</hi> as Chriſt commanded his Apoſtles, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their <hi>Succeſſors</hi> the Paſtors of his Church, to the end of the World; yet where Men are ſo <hi>obſtinate,</hi> as to reject all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, they are taught to go elſewhere, and only to <hi>pity</hi> and <hi>pray</hi> for ſuch blind Souls, but not to <hi>deſtroy them.</hi> 'Tis true, in the <hi>Catholic Church</hi> care is taken, to preſerve all ſuch as are her <hi>Members,</hi> firm in her Communion; and there are not wanting <hi>Threats</hi> to keep the <hi>Inconſtant</hi> from being Miſled into <hi>Error;</hi> as likewiſe <hi>Puniſhments</hi> to reduce ſuch as leave her, and blindly run after <hi>Falſe Guides.</hi> And if for this reaſon ſhe muſt be ſaid to <hi>tear out their Hearts,</hi> and <hi>deſtroy ſuch as ſhe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deceive:</hi> what is to be the Character of this <hi>Preacher's Church,</hi> which, by conſent of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> is fenc'd with ſuch <hi>Laws,</hi> as puniſhes with <hi>Loſs of Goods, Impriſonment,</hi> and <hi>Death,</hi> not
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:65446:26"/> only thoſe who <hi>leave her Communion,</hi> but likewiſe thoſe too who never were <hi>Members</hi> of it. This is a <hi>Cruelty</hi> not to be paralell'd amongſt the worſt of Chriſtians. I cannot ſay, but that <hi>Raſh Zeal, Headlong Revenge,</hi> or <hi>Deteſtable Avarice,</hi> may have hurried ſome of ours upon ſuch <hi>Barbarous Attempts;</hi> but certainly never did any Chriſtians <hi>deliberately</hi> and with <hi>Counſel,</hi> thus deeply engage themſelves in <hi>Blood.</hi> 'Tis one thing to <hi>ſhed Blood</hi> in the heat of <hi>Fury</hi> and <hi>Paſſion,</hi> another thing to do it by <hi>Law,</hi> and if ours are thus to be condemn'd of <hi>Cruelty</hi> for ſome <hi>Raſh</hi> and unaccountable Practices of this kind, which we deteſt upon Reflection; certainly others have a better Title to this <hi>Infamous Mark,</hi> who with ſuch Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, both in <hi>Goods, Liberty</hi> and <hi>Life,</hi> puniſh thoſe with <hi>Delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> who never were of their Communion; and are ſo zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in maintaining thoſe <hi>Laws</hi> in force, by which they own themſelves <hi>Bloody</hi> by <hi>Profeſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>The Abſurdity of Auricular Confeſſion is endleſs, where a Man unlades himſelf of all his Sins, by whiſpering them into Prieſts Ears.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This again is a <hi>Calumny</hi> and <hi>Miſrepreſentation,</hi> ſince no <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholics</hi> teach, that <hi>only Whiſpering Sins in the Ears of a Prieſt</hi> is ſufficient for their Remiſſion. They own indeed <hi>Confeſſion to a Prieſt</hi> in order to Abſolution, and the ſame is allow'd by the <hi>Church of England;</hi> but beſides this <hi>Whiſpering,</hi> they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire likewiſe a <hi>True</hi> and <hi>Hearty Sorrow,</hi> joyn'd with a <hi>Firm Purpoſe of Amendment,</hi> and a <hi>Sincere Reſolution</hi> of <hi>avoiding,</hi> thro' the help of God's Grace, all <hi>Sins</hi> and the occaſion of them for the future: and this I hope, as no body will deny to be a proper Means, in order to Forgiveneſs; ſo likewiſe every one will ſee how unſincere this <hi>Preacher</hi> was in ſaying, <hi>That a Man unlades himſelf of all his Sins by whiſpering them into Prieſts ears,</hi> To make his Followers believe the <hi>Papiſts</hi> to be ſo <hi>Sottiſh,</hi> as to think their Sins forgiven by a <hi>Whiſper</hi> only.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Of Tranſubſtantiation, where Men muſt renounce all their Five Senſes at once.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How is this true, that we muſt <hi>renounce all our Five Senſes</hi> in the belief of this <hi>Myſtery;</hi> ſince, if we follow our <hi>Hearing,</hi> which is the <hi>Senſe</hi> by which <hi>Faith</hi> comes, we are oblig'd to believe it? <hi>Chriſt's Words</hi> expreſly ſignifie and declare, that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:65446:27"/> the <hi>Sacrament is his Body.</hi> Theſe <hi>Words</hi> we <hi>hear</hi> deliver'd to us by thoſe, whom He has appointed to <hi>Teach</hi> and <hi>Inſtruct</hi> the <hi>Flock,</hi> to wit, the <hi>Paſtors</hi> of Chriſt's <hi>Church:</hi> theſe <hi>Words</hi> we <hi>ſee</hi> likewiſe and <hi>read</hi> in the <hi>Holy Scripture.</hi> So that if we fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low our <hi>Ears</hi> and our <hi>Eyes</hi> directed by the <hi>Word of God,</hi> we are bound to believe this <hi>Myſtery,</hi> and conſequently do not <hi>renounce all Five at once.</hi> And thus, whilſt we let both our <hi>Senſes</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> be immediately directed by <hi>God's Word,</hi> which is <hi>Infallible,</hi> we more Reverence the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve</hi> upon better Grounds, than <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> who let <hi>Natural Objects,</hi> ever about Myſteries of their Faith, have the direction of their <hi>Senſes,</hi> in which they are ſo often deceiv'd, rather than the <hi>Word of God,</hi> which cannot deceive them. We ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that to frame a <hi>Judgment</hi> of the <hi>Nature</hi> or <hi>Subſtance</hi> of a thing, we muſt depend upon the Information of <hi>Senſe,</hi> and that the <hi>Common</hi> and <hi>Natural</hi> way, is to Judge according to the Relation the <hi>Senſes</hi> give, from the <hi>External</hi> and <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Accidents</hi> of the thing. But if we deſire to frame a True Judgment, of what is the <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Subſtance</hi> of ſuch an Object, not according to a <hi>Natural Being,</hi> but according to the <hi>Divine Power,</hi> and what it may have of <hi>Supernatural;</hi> the <hi>Senſes</hi> ought not to be laid aſide, but we muſt conſider here too the Information Theſe give, not now from the <hi>Natural Accidents,</hi> but from the <hi>Word of God,</hi> and the <hi>Divine Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation;</hi> for tho' the <hi>Natural Subſtance</hi> of the thing be connected with, and beſt known by its <hi>Natural Qualities,</hi> yet a <hi>Superna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Being</hi> not ſo; and therefore This is better known from what the <hi>Senſes</hi> tell us from <hi>God's Word,</hi> and <hi>Divine Revelation,</hi> than from the <hi>External Accidents</hi> and <hi>Natural Qualities</hi> of the thing. I illuſtrate this by an Inſtance in another matter: If I have a <hi>Preſent</hi> ſent me in a Letter by a Friend, and I intend to make a Judgment of the <hi>True Nature</hi> of it, and <hi>What it is;</hi> I cannot do this without the aſſiſtance of my <hi>Senſes.</hi> But then Theſe may inform me <hi>Two ways;</hi> either by <hi>Looking</hi> upon the thing it ſelf, (which at preſent I ſuppoſe is a <hi>Tranſparent Stone)</hi> obſerving every <hi>Caſt</hi> of the <hi>Light,</hi> how <hi>Pale,</hi> &amp;c. or by <hi>Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> the Letter, which being ſent from an <hi>Excellent Artiſt,</hi> gives a full Account of it; as likewiſe <hi>Hearing</hi> What the Bearer ſays, whom I know to be a skilful <hi>Jeweller.</hi> Now in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:65446:27"/> both theſe ways I uſe my <hi>Senſes</hi> in order to <hi>Judge</hi> of the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,</hi> as to its <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Value.</hi> If I take the Information of my <hi>Senſes,</hi> from the View of the <hi>Stone</hi> in it ſelf; I <hi>Judge</hi> it, to the beſt of my Skill, to be <hi>no Precious Stone,</hi> but ſome <hi>Counterfeit</hi> or <hi>Peble:</hi> If I take the Information my <hi>Senſes</hi> give me from the <hi>Reading</hi> the Letter, and <hi>Hearing</hi> the Artiſt; I <hi>Judge</hi> it to be a <hi>True Diamond,</hi> upon their Authority and greater Skill, who being of known Honeſty, do unfeignedly give me this Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. Now in which Judgment of theſe ought In in Prudence finally to acquieſe? Certainly in this laſt. And yet in ſo doing, I hope I ſhould not <hi>renounce all my Five Senſes at once.</hi> No, even in this Judgment too I ſhould depend upon my <hi>Senſes.</hi> And if in ſuch a Caſe as this I prudently form my <hi>Judgment,</hi> from the Account my <hi>Senſes</hi> give me of ſuch Mens Authority and Knowledge, rather than from my own, becauſe the <hi>Nature</hi> of the Thing before me, conſiſts in ſomething a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove my Skill: Certainly, when the Queſtion is, <hi>What is the Subſtance</hi> or <hi>Eſſence</hi> of a thing, not <hi>Natural,</hi> but Reveal'd to be <hi>Miraculous,</hi> and according to the <hi>Divine Power and Ordinance?</hi> the Safeſt Judgment ought to be fram'd, not from what my <hi>Senſes</hi> tell me of the <hi>Natural Accidents,</hi> but from what They tell me of <hi>God's Word,</hi> and the <hi>Divine Aſſurance;</hi> becauſe, as Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> ſays, <hi>(Preſerv. againſt Pop. p.</hi> 25.) <hi>We may rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably conclude, that God underſtands the Reaſons and Nature of things, better than we.</hi> Since therefore my <hi>Senſes</hi> aſſure me from <hi>Scripture</hi> and the <hi>Paſtor</hi>'s of God's Church, that the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament</hi> is <hi>Chriſt's Body:</hi> I am bound in <hi>Reaſon</hi> to Judge, it <hi>Is ſo;</hi> rather than from the <hi>Natural Accidents,</hi> to Judge it to be <hi>Bread.</hi> So that in thus Believing this Myſtery, we do not <hi>Renounce,</hi> but <hi>Follow</hi> our <hi>Senſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, <hi>The Pope alone cannot Err, and All others, without ſome of his Aſſiſtance, cannot but Err.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This again is abſolutely Falſe: For tho' <hi>Catholics</hi> Believe, that the <hi>Catholic</hi> Church, whether <hi>Diffuſive,</hi> or in its <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives,</hi> viz. a General Aſſembly of Biſhops under their <hi>Head</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> thro' the Divine Aſſiſtance of the Holy Spirit, cannot Err in declaring Matters of Faith: and ſome <hi>School-Divines</hi> are of Opinion, that the <hi>Pope</hi> is aſſiſted with a like Infallible Direction, even at other times. Yet
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:65446:28"/> never did any <hi>Catholics</hi> Teach or Believe, that all others, without the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Aſſiſtance, were under a <hi>Neceſſity of Erring.</hi> No <hi>Determinations</hi> indeed of others, without his Conſent, are of <hi>Force</hi> or <hi>Obligatory</hi> on the <hi>Whole Church,</hi> no more than is a Vote of <hi>Parliament,</hi> without the Approbation of the <hi>King,</hi> a <hi>Law</hi> to the <hi>Nation.:</hi> Yet there's no neceſſity of Concluding them <hi>Falſe and Erroneous;</hi> but only <hi>Not Authentic. Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> believe their own <hi>Church</hi> not to be <hi>Infallible;</hi> and yet they don't think it to lie under a <hi>Neceſſity of Erring.</hi> Why therefore muſt it be charg'd upon us, becauſe we believe the <hi>Members</hi> of our Church, without their <hi>Head,</hi> to be <hi>Fallible,</hi> that Therefore <hi>They cannot but Err?</hi> This therefore is a moſt Illogical and Abſurd Conſequence, ſuch as the <hi>Apologizer</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf knows not how to juſtifie, and yet he has not Goodneſs enough to acquit us from ſo foul a Calumny.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="character">
               <head>Eighth Character of a Pulpit-Papiſt.</head>
               <argument>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>HE is profeſſedly edified in Ignorance by his Church, Praying</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Dr. Standiſh <hi>ibid.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>and Propheſying in an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nknown Tongue. They make no other uſe or account of Confeſſion, than what profeſſed Drunkards do of Vomiting.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </argument>
               <p>Thus is his Religion deſcrib'd in a Sermon before the <hi>Judges</hi> at <hi>Hertford</hi> 1682/3. but moſt abuſively. 1. For tho' the <hi>Maſs</hi> is ſaid in <hi>Latin</hi> by the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> yet the <hi>People</hi> have it tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh;</hi> they have it expounded in ſeveral Books at large, and are taught to underſtand, and have a true Senſe of what is done; ſo that if they are <hi>Ignorant,</hi> 'tis to be imputed to their own Neglect, and not to any Deſign in their Church, which is ſo careful in providing all neceſſary Means for the avoiding that Inconvenience. But of this more afterwards. But his Church, beſides <hi>Praying, Propheſies too,</hi> ſays the <hi>Preacher, in an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nknown Tongue.</hi> Here the <hi>Apologizer p.</hi> 20. is put to it, to ſave the Credit of the <hi>Preacher:</hi> He owns that by <hi>Propheſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> is meant in S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Cor. 14. <hi>Expounding the Scripture and Articles of Faith to the People,</hi> and to be the ſame as <hi>Preaching:</hi> and knowing, that <hi>Catholics</hi> do this in the <hi>Vulgar Language;</hi> if
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:65446:28"/> the <hi>Preacher</hi> be underſtood in this common Senſe of the Word, he cannot excuſe him, from abuſing his Auditory with a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny. <hi>But,</hi> ſays the Apologizer, <hi>it do's not appear to me that the Preacher here underſtood it of vulgar Preaching, becauſe he knew it to be otherwiſe.</hi> Marry, if They never Preach'd contrary to what they knew, this would be a good Rule. But ſuppoſe he did not; yet he impoſes upon his <hi>Hearers,</hi> whilſt he aſſerts a thing of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> which in the <hi>common acceptation</hi> of the Word is <hi>abſolutely Falſe;</hi> and yet leaves it to them to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken as they pleaſe. And therefore whilſt he ſays <hi>abſolutely,</hi> that <hi>They Propheſie in an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nknown Tongue,</hi> which is the ſame as <hi>Preaching,</hi> he Miſrepreſents the <hi>Papiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>They make no other uſe or account of Confeſſion, than what profeſs'd Drunkards do of Vomiting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is a moſt Putid Calumny: and the <hi>Vindicator</hi> is ſo ſenſible of it, <hi>p.</hi> 21. that he dares not defend, what the <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> aſſerts; but only, that ſo it is in the <hi>Practice of many of their Church.</hi> This indeed we don't doubt, but many in <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice</hi> abuſe <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> as they do all other <hi>Good things:</hi> but how different is it to ſay, That <hi>many Papiſts abuſe Confeſſion,</hi> and That <hi>the Papiſts abſolutely make</hi> NO OTHER <hi>uſe of Confeſſion, than what profeſs'd Drunkards do of Vomiting.</hi> The <hi>former,</hi> I fear is too <hi>True,</hi> but the <hi>later</hi> is <hi>Falſe,</hi> and a thing that no modeſt Man can ſay, without Bluſhing, out of a <hi>Pulpit.</hi> It may be as truly ſaid, That the <hi>Miniſters of the Church of</hi> England <hi>make no other uſe of Preaching, than what the</hi> Profeſs'd Enemies <hi>of the Crown do of Libelling,</hi> viz. <hi>to fill the People witb Fears and Jealouſies, and diſaffect them towards the King and Government.</hi> And then after ſuch an Aſperſion, what a Come-off would it be, to ſay, I mean this only of the <hi>Practice</hi> of ſome of that Profeſſion? This is the Caſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="character">
               <head>Ninth Character of a Pulpit-Papiſt.</head>
               <argument>
                  <q>
                     <p>1. <hi>HE pays his Devotions to Saints Canoniz'd for Money and</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">J. Turner <hi>ib.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Treaſon.</hi> 2. <hi>In his Church they Pray to the Crucifix of Wood or Stone, as well as to Chriſt himſelf, and attribute as much Satisfaction and Expiation to it, as they do to the Blood of</hi>
                        <pb n="36" facs="tcp:65446:29"/> 
                        <hi>their Crucifi'd Redeemer.</hi> 3. <hi>Their Confeſſion, inſtead of keeping up a Wholſom Diſcipline, is the way to corrupt it, and tends to the Debauching both Laity and Clergy.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </argument>
               <p>This is <hi>Popery,</hi> as Painted out at <hi>Lincolns-Inn, Sep.</hi> 29. 1683. As to the Firſt Point, it is only inſinuated by the Preacher, with an <hi>It is not lawful to Pray,</hi> &amp;c. which is as good as an <hi>Aſſertion</hi> to the Hearers, viz. <hi>That the Papiſts do Pray to Saints Canoniz'd for Treaſon.</hi> The <hi>Vindicator,</hi> to make this good, proves Firſt, That <hi>it may ſo happen, that</hi> Saints may be Canoniz'd for Treaſon. Which is as much to the purpoſe, as for one to ſay, That the <hi>Church-of-England-men</hi> are <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupters of God's Word,</hi> becauſe, <hi>'tis poſſible they may be ſo;</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their Principles <hi>Fallible,</hi> as to what they Teach and Preach to their Flock. Secondly, he'll prove that <hi>it has been done;</hi> and then comes in the next Line with an Inſtance, in which it <hi>had like to have been done,</hi> as he ſays, but <hi>was not done.</hi> Laſtly, he ſays, that <hi>Thomas à Becket</hi> was Canoniz'd for <hi>Rebellion,</hi> becauſe he adher'd to the <hi>Pope</hi> againſt his Prince. No, 'twas for his <hi>Vertuous Life</hi> and <hi>Martyrdom,</hi> and the atte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of his Sanctity by undeniable Miracles. 'Tis not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hering to the Pope is enough to be Canoniz'd after Death. But if adhering to the Pope was Rebellion in that Biſhop, what do's he think of a Doctor, who adheres to a <hi>Neighboring State,</hi> againſt his Liege Prince? And what of Thoſe others here at home, who help to ſpread, and are ſo ſatisfi'd in <hi>Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Libels,</hi> deſign'd on purpoſe againſt the King and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment? Beſides their Induſtry to uphold, in open oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to their Sovereign, a <hi>Device,</hi> which was laid by ill Men, on deſign to exclude his Preſent Majeſty from the Crown? If <hi>Thomas à Becket</hi> was a <hi>Traitor,</hi> for adhering to the Pope in ſome Eccleſiaſtical Privileges, how far from Traitors and Rebels are Theſe, who joyn Hands with declar'd Traitors, and eſpouſe the ſame Cauſe againſt their Prince? How might this be ſet out, if there were but Ten thouſand Pulpits to Paint it to the beſt Advantage?</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>They Pray to a Crucifix of Wood or Stone, as well as to Chriſt himſelf, and attribute as much Satisfaction to it, as to the Blood of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:65446:29"/>
               <p> This is every word an Infamous Falſhood. And tho' the Vindicator here to acquit the Preacher, from caſting ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, and worſe than Heatheniſh Scandal upon us, appeals to the <hi>Words</hi> and <hi>Forms</hi> of ſome of our Prayers; and then ſays, That if <hi>Words will make it plain, the Preacher was not miſtaken, pag.</hi> 24. Yet this is ſo childiſh a Plea, that me-thinks it ought to be beneath a <hi>Divine,</hi> eſpecially a Man of Conſcience, to charge ſo <hi>Groſs</hi> an <hi>Abomination</hi> upon ſuch a Frothy Pretext. For what if there are ſome Words in our Addreſſes, that, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken literally, import as much? Is this any more than what is found in Scripture, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 1. where <hi>Moſes</hi> thus cries out, <hi>Give ear, O ye Heavens, and I will ſpeak; and hear, O Earth, the words of my mouth?</hi> Is <hi>Moſes,</hi> for this Form, preſently to be accus'd of Calling upon the Material <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> to hear him? If this way of Arguing were enough, pray, what might be ſaid of the <hi>Church of England</hi> too? A Controvertiſt, with a <hi>Forehead</hi> to the Temper of one of Thoſe who makes up againſt us, might poſitively accuſe her in her <hi>Solemn Devotion,</hi> and moſt <hi>Religious</hi> Way of <hi>Worſhip,</hi> of Addreſſing themſelves to the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon, Stars, Showrs,</hi> and <hi>Winds;</hi> and calling upon, to their Aſſiſtance, the <hi>Birds,</hi> the <hi>Beaſts,</hi> and the <hi>Fiſhes.</hi> And then for to make all this good beyond exception, he has no more to do, than to make this Plea: that, <hi>This being a Charge of Words and Forms, we muſt know, whether the Charge be True or Falſe, by conſidering thoſe Forms; and if Words will make it plain, the Arguer is not miſtaken.</hi> For ſee all this in their <hi>Canti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle Benedicite</hi> in the <hi>Morning Prayer.</hi> What Stuff is this? And yet theſe are ſome of the Methods, which the <hi>Church of England</hi> takes up to juſtifie her ſelf, to defame her Mother-Church, and to fill the World with Confuſion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Making a Particular Confeſſion of our Sins to Men, inſtead of keeping up wholſom Diſcipline, is the way to corrupt it, and tends to the Debauching both Laity and Clergy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To ſee whither an Indiſcreet Zeal, and Blind Paſſion hurries Men, even to the <hi>blackning</hi> their <hi>own Church,</hi> whilſt they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigh againſt their Neighbors! Thus infamouſly is <hi>Confeſſion</hi> painted out; and yet this very <hi>Auricular Confeſſion</hi> was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd to all, and at all times, as a good <hi>Proteſtant Practice,</hi> in the <hi>Firſt Common-Prayer-Book</hi> of <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth. And the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:65446:30"/> 
                  <hi>Church of England</hi> now at this time <hi>refuſes no ſort of Confeſſion,</hi> as the Expounder of her Doctrins ſays, <hi>p.</hi> 42. <hi>whether Public</hi> or <hi>Private.</hi> And even now in her preſent <hi>Liturgy,</hi> is the <hi>Miniſter</hi> order'd, in the <hi>Viſitation of the Sick,</hi> to move the <hi>Sick Perſon to make a Special Confeſſion of his Sins.</hi> Certainly if it were true, as the Preacher ſays, that <hi>Confeſſion</hi> tends to the <hi>Debauching both Laity and Clergy,</hi> his <hi>Church</hi> is very much to blame, for appointing ſuch a Preparative for Death, and ordering its Members thus to be Debauch'd at the laſt hour. But this I conſider as the <hi>Preacher's Heat,</hi> who inſtead of reproving ſome <hi>Abuſes,</hi> thus blindly falls foul upon the Beſt of Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. And the Apologizer has the Grace to follow him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="character">
               <head>Tenth Character of a Pulpit-Papiſt.</head>
               <argument>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>THE Churches Intereſt is the Center of Their Religion, and</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">W. Wray <hi>ib.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Their Conſciences turn upon the ſame Pin. Every thing is Pious, Conſcientious and Meritorious, that makes for their Cauſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </argument>
               <p>In this Colour was <hi>Popery</hi> ſet out in the Year 1682. A time when the <hi>Church of England</hi> was with ſuch blind <hi>Zeal</hi> and <hi>Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> both in <hi>Desk</hi> and <hi>Pulpit</hi> purſuing her own <hi>Intereſt</hi> in the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Defeating the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> that if the Preacher had turn'd his Eyes nearer home, he might have ſeen <hi>Himſelf,</hi> and his <hi>Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> an <hi>Inſtance</hi> of that <hi>Crime,</hi> he was even then charging upon his Adverſaries. And tho' the Apologizer will have this True of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> by a wreſted Interpretation of a Conſtitution of the Fathers of the <hi>Society,</hi> contrary to the plain meaning of it. Yet after that, and all he can ſay, he cannot but own it to be <hi>a receiv'd Maxim</hi> amongſt <hi>all,</hi> even the <hi>Looſeſt</hi> of our Divines and Caſuiſts, that <hi>No Evil is to be done, that Good may come of it.</hi> And there's no <hi>Proteſtant</hi> but, upon Reflection, may call to mind, how Religiouſly the <hi>Catholics</hi> of this Nation have obſerv'd it, who, for ſo many Years, have been excluded the moſt conſiderable Places of <hi>Honor, Truſt</hi> and <hi>Profit,</hi> which might have been ſo much to their own <hi>Private Advantage,</hi> as likewiſe to that of <hi>their Church;</hi> and yet have quietly and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly quitted them all, rather than do an ill thing, take <hi>Oaths,</hi>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:65446:30"/> 
                  <hi>Teſts,</hi> or <hi>go to Church,</hi> againſt their Conſcience. Thus have they acted like the Beſt of Chriſtians in the face of the World, without reſpect to the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of themſelves or their <hi>Church;</hi> and yet, upon I know not what Speculation and <hi>Pulpit-Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences,</hi> are they moſt unjuſtly render'd, as Men without Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, as moving only upon Intereſt, and ſcrupling at no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, nay making the worſt of things <hi>Meritorious,</hi> ſo it be but for the Advantage of Mother-Church. <hi>Wicked Men</hi> of his Church, as of any other, may act upon ſuch Principles, but to ſet out his <hi>Religion</hi> in theſe Colours, is a moſt Abuſive Slander, and more becoming the Rudeneſs of <hi>Street-Lectures,</hi> than the Gravity and Sincerity, that ought to be in the <hi>Pulpit.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="character">
               <head>Eleventh Character of a Pulpit Papiſt.</head>
               <argument>
                  <q>
                     <p>1. <hi>HE changes Scripture into Legends.</hi> 2. <hi>Sacraments into</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">N. Bisby <hi>ib.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Shews, Prieſts into Puppets.</hi> 3. <hi>Preaches Purgatory inſtead of Repentance.</hi> 4. <hi>Faction inſtead of Faith; never minds the Lawfulneſs of the Means, provided the thing be but done.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </argument>
               <p>Thus was the <hi>Papiſt</hi> drawn in 1683. but without <hi>Truth</hi> or <hi>Charity:</hi> every Line being either abſolutely Falſe, or drawn with ſo much Diſingenuity, that no more would be requir'd to make the <hi>Beſt</hi> of things <hi>Ridiculous.</hi> For how do's the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt</hi> change the <hi>Scripture</hi> into <hi>Legends:</hi> when he is commanded by his <hi>Church,</hi> to own the <hi>Scripture</hi> as the <hi>Word of God,</hi> and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to aſſent to <hi>all</hi> therein deliver'd, as of <hi>Divine Authority,</hi> and of <hi>neceſſity</hi> to be <hi>believ'd</hi> with a <hi>Divine Faith:</hi> whilſt for <hi>Legends,</hi> tho' he may read them if he pleaſes, as he do's other <hi>Hiſtories,</hi> yet he is not bound by his <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Religion,</hi> to give <hi>aſſent</hi> to, or <hi>believe</hi> any <hi>one Paſſage,</hi> in any <hi>Legend</hi> whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever? This the Apologizer underſtood very well, <hi>pag.</hi> 23. where he proves out of <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and <hi>Canus,</hi> that according to our <hi>own Principles,</hi> all theſe things contain'd in the <hi>Lives of Saints,</hi> tho' mention'd even in the Canonization, depend upon <hi>Human Teſtimony,</hi> as to particular Matters of Fact, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently are ſubject to <hi>Error.</hi> And therefore no ſufficient
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:65446:31"/> ground for any Point of Faith, which can be built on nothing leſs than <hi>Divine Authority.</hi> And tho' ſome of theſe are inſerted into our <hi>Offices,</hi> yet they are not there propos'd (as likewiſe <hi>Particular Revelations)</hi> as the <hi>Scripture</hi> is, to wit, as matter of <hi>Faith,</hi> but only as a Relation of ſome Hiſtory, in the Reading of which, ſome Spiritual Advantage may be reap'd; as is at large diſcours'd above. Which is very different from what the Preacher ſays, that <hi>he changes Scripture into Legends.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. How do's he change the <hi>Sacraments</hi> into <hi>Shows,</hi> when in his Church the <hi>Sacraments</hi> are not only <hi>Shewn,</hi> but likewiſe care taken, that they be duly Adminiſtred to all her <hi>Members?</hi> The <hi>Apologizer</hi> pretends the Charge to be True; becauſe the <hi>Cup</hi> is ſhew'd to the People, which they don't partake of; and the <hi>Hoſt</hi> elevated at <hi>Maſs,</hi> and carry'd in Proceſſion. And might not a <hi>Jew</hi> here ſtep in, and with this Argument pretend, that <hi>Chriſt Crucifi'd</hi> was another <hi>Show</hi> upon <hi>Calvary,</hi> while he was there expos'd for ſome hours upon the <hi>Croſs</hi> to the view of the World? But all this is nothing but a Method to teach <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> how to make the greateſt Myſteries of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity Ridiculous. We know the Benefit of that <hi>Oblation</hi> Chriſt made of his Body and Blood upon the <hi>Croſs,</hi> and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of that he Inſtituted at his <hi>Laſt Supper,</hi> where he gave his Body and Blood after an Unbloody manner, under the Forms of Bread and Wine for the <hi>Remiſſion of Sins;</hi> and which is now daily repeated in the Church, according to the Command of Chriſt, which he gave to his Apoſtles, when he ſaid to them, <hi>DO THIS in Remembrance of me;</hi> We know the Benefit there is in this <hi>Continual Remembrance.</hi> And thoſe, who make a <hi>Show</hi> of this, are within one Step of thoſe <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelieving Jews,</hi> who made a <hi>Show</hi> of Chriſt in his Paſſion, when 'twas ſaid to them, <hi>Behold the Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. As for the <hi>Third,</hi> of <hi>Preaching Purgatory inſtead of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,</hi> 'tis abſolutely Falſe, inaſmuch as in the plain import of the words, it imprints this Notion in the Hearers; <hi>viz. That the Papiſts don't Preach Repentance to the People, but inſtead of this they Preach Purgatory.</hi> This, I ſay, is Falſe, and ſo evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently, that the Apologizer dares not vindicate the Preacher in ſo foul a Calumny: and therefore inſtead of what the <hi>Preacher</hi> aſſerts, the <hi>Vindicator</hi> minces the matter, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:65446:31"/> only, <hi>that the Doctrin of Purgatory invalidates that of Repentance.</hi> Which too is Falſe in it ſelf, ſince we ſee <hi>Catholics</hi> both in their <hi>Lives,</hi> their <hi>Books</hi> and <hi>Sermons,</hi> urge the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of <hi>Repentance</hi> as much and as effectually as <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> And 'tis much more Falſe as to <hi>Preaching,</hi> ſince amongſt ſo many Sermons I have been at, both Abroad, and in our own Country, I have heard <hi>Repentance</hi> ſo often preſs'd to the People; and <hi>Purgatory</hi> never ſo much as mention'd, unleſs it were to ſhew the inſufferable Torments of the Place, and how great the hazard is, even of getting thither. And amongſt the Printed Sermons of <hi>Spaniards, French, Portugueſe,</hi> &amp;c. that are extant in <hi>Latin,</hi> I challenge the Apologizer to find one that ſo ſets out <hi>Purgatory</hi> to the People, as to make them neglect <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance:</hi> and if he do's, I'll be bound to ſhew him a Hundred for his One, that enforce the Duty of <hi>Repenting,</hi> without the leaſt hint of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> or their conſiding in it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. He ſays, <hi>We Preach Faction inſtead of Faith,</hi> &amp;c. This the Preacher ſaid of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> at a time, when the <hi>Church of England</hi> had been aſſiſting a <hi>Faction</hi> about <hi>Four Years,</hi> with all the help the <hi>Pulpit</hi> could give them, in Conſecrating their <hi>Villanies,</hi> and finding Arguments to gain them <hi>Credit,</hi> for the deluding the People. And tho' they cannot be <hi>Advis'd</hi> to be more <hi>Cautious</hi> for the future, without an <hi>Apology</hi> appearing in their behalf; yet I hope, 'tis not without ſome <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Shame;</hi> eſpecially ſince they have ſeen the <hi>Cart</hi> and <hi>Pillory</hi> ſo often appearing in Confutation of thoſe <hi>Truths</hi> that were then ſo often Diſpens'd to the People with the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> As for the <hi>Faction</hi> they can diſcover in <hi>Our Preaching,</hi> let them do their beſt, to find even <hi>half</hi> ſo much; we freely give them a <hi>Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Years</hi> to review, for to match theſe <hi>Four</hi> of theirs. Let them take in likewiſe the <hi>Sermons,</hi> that are now Preach'd in our <hi>Chappels</hi> throughout the Kingdom. I hope they'll all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear Inſtructive as to <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Manners,</hi> but free from <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi> Can the <hi>Church of England</hi> ſay as much of theirs at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, in which there are ſo many unworthy <hi>Reflections</hi> made upon the <hi>Religion</hi> of their <hi>Prince;</hi> ſo much <hi>Animoſity</hi> blown up, <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealouſies</hi> inſinuated into the People, and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment made to them <hi>uneaſie,</hi> even in the very Method that diſpos'd them heretofore to <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and ended not, but with
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:65446:32"/> the Murder of their Sovereign? I can't imagine them to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the like Miſchief at preſent; neither did they, I believe, heretofore, when they made way for it, by their <hi>Indiſcreet Preaching.</hi> But when they have ſeen ſo lately the People ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperated to that degree by the <hi>Pulpits</hi> againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> as even in an Unnatural Rebellion to take up Arms againſt their Prince, and never leave purſuing him under the Pretext of his being a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> till they had brought his Royal Head to the Block under the ſame Notion: Methinks ſuch as are <hi>truly Loyal,</hi> and boaſt themſelves the <hi>Beſt Subjects</hi> in the World, ſhould be more Tender of their <hi>Sovereign,</hi> than to venture upon the ſame Method with the <hi>Son,</hi> which prov'd ſo <hi>Fatal</hi> to the <hi>Father,</hi> and ſo <hi>Dangerous</hi> to the <hi>Brother.</hi> But I fear the <hi>Exceſs of Jealouſie</hi> for their Religion, puts them upon being too Bold with their <hi>Prince;</hi> and that by a Juſt Judgment of Heaven, they are blindly <hi>practiſing</hi> the very <hi>Principles</hi> they have ſo often charg'd upon the <hi>Papiſts; Making their Church's Intereſt the Center of their Religion; Preaching Faction inſtead of Faith; Eſteeming everything Conſcientious that makes for the Cauſe; And not minding the Lawfulneſs of the Means, provided the Thing be but done.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="character">
               <head>Twelfth Character of a Pulpit-Papiſt.</head>
               <argument>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>THERE is a great noiſe of Alms made in his Church; but the Scope they too often vainly aim at, is the Bleſſing of a</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Dr. Teniſon. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Preſumed Saint; Security from the external force of Evil Spirits, by the Charms and Spells of Monkiſh Conjuration, a ſort of Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Magic. Nay, ſometimes the Scope is that very wicked one of Compounding with Heaven by their Liberal Alms, for their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forſaken Sins; and here in this Nation (whilſt this Iſland was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanted with Popery) there were granted Indulgences even for what they call Deadly Sins, for many Thouſand Years to come.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </argument>
               <p>In this manner did Dr. <hi>Teniſon</hi> render our Religion at S. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher's</hi> 1681. before the Honorable Magiſtrates of this <hi>City,</hi> in a Strain ſo unbecoming, that every ordinary Reader upon the Peruſal, muſt neceſſarily be tempted to turn to the Title
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:65446:32"/> Page, to ſee whether it bears <hi>Sermon</hi> or <hi>Play.</hi> And therefore I think the Doctor, upon Reflection, might have rather given me Thanks, than quarrell'd, for my not inſerting <hi>more</hi> of his Diſcourſe; ſince, I am confident, the leſs I put in, was more for his Credit. But however, <hi>another Author</hi> has ſince done him that Right, as to tranſcribe him, and ſet him out more at <note place="margin">Diſquiſit. and Expoſtul. with the Church of Engl.</note> length: let him view himſelf there drawn to the full, and then let him tell me, whether he be not oblig'd to me, for ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him but <hi>in Little.</hi> I refer the Reader thither to be Judge, and in the mean time I'll throw away a Page upon him in the Examen of his Vindication; where I no ſooner caſt my Eye, but I ſee that being now a <hi>Doctor,</hi> he underſtands no more Our Doctrin or Practice, than, when he was a Child, he knew <hi>Gubbard</hi> from a <hi>Jeſuit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. He ſays, <hi>Sometimes the Scope is, that very Wicked one, of Compounding with Heaven by their Liberal Alms, for their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forſaken Sins.</hi> This he poſitively and ſolemnly declar'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo Great an Aſſembly, but without one word of Proof in the Sermon for ſo foul a Charge: and now when he takes upon him, to make his <hi>Defence,</hi> he only proves at large the Practice of <hi>Indulgences,</hi> but not a word of their being given for <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nforſaken Sins,</hi> which is the chief Point of his ſo ſcandalous Aſperſion. We own the Power of granting <hi>Indulgences</hi> or <hi>Pardons,</hi> as may be ſeen in our Profeſſion of Faith; but that this can or may be done, either with Money or without, for <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nforſaken Sins,</hi> this we look upon as Abominable and Abſurd, in the ſight both of God and Man. And amongſt all that Liſt of <hi>Pardons,</hi> he has heap'd up in his <hi>Defence,</hi> there is not one that he can pretend, makes for this intent, excepting that of <hi>Boniface</hi> 9. which too has nothing in it for his purpoſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides his own <hi>Falſe Tranſlation,</hi> and the <hi>Perverſe Conſtruction</hi> he puts upon it, the Effect I hope more of his <hi>Ignorance</hi> than his <hi>Malice.</hi> Since thoſe words quoted by him, <hi>Omnia Peccata etiam SINE POENITENTIA ipſis Confitentibus relaxarunt,</hi> do not ſignifie the giving <hi>Indulgence for all Sins WITH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T REPENTANCE,</hi> as he tranſlates them; but only the granting Indulgence for all Sins, to ſuch as <hi>Confeſs'd</hi> to them without obliging them to undergo the <hi>Penances</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd by the <hi>Canons:</hi> for thus this word <hi>Poenitentia</hi> here ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:65446:33"/> and not <hi>Repentance,</hi> which is indiſpenſably imply'd in their <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> which cannot be rightly perform'd without <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi> Thus groſly do's this Doctor miſtake in his Defence, and upon ſuch ſlight Grounds, poſitively from his <hi>Pulpit,</hi> blacken us with the worſt of Infamy and Scandal, before ſo Great an Aſſembly. And the ſame he do's in the other part, where he ſays,</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>That they have granted Indulgences even for what they call Deadly Sins, for many Thouſand Years to come.</hi> And this looks like an Aſſerting of that <hi>Vulgar Reproach,</hi> to wit, <hi>That the Pope can give the Papiſts leave to ſin for many Years to come;</hi> and is the thing he ſeems willing to imprint on his Readers, in all the Inſtances he has brought, by the way that he handles them. And yet this is moſt contradictory to the Doctrin we are taught, and to the receiv'd Notion of <hi>Indulgences</hi> amongſt <hi>Catholics,</hi> who are ſo far from preſuming upon <hi>Leave to ſin,</hi> upon the grant of <hi>Indulgences,</hi> that they don't think, that any <hi>One Sin that is paſt,</hi> can be forgiven by an <hi>Indulgence.</hi> No, we are taught, that no Sin is forgiven, even in the Sacrament of <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> without a ſincere Repentance. And as for <hi>Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> they are only for the Relaxation of the <hi>Canonical Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> due to <hi>Sin;</hi> which being appointed and aſſign'd by the Church, may likewiſe, by the ſame Authority, be releas'd. And therefore, however <hi>Indulgences</hi> may be term'd <hi>Pardons,</hi> or ſaid to be granted for the obtaining <hi>Pardon for Deadly ſins;</hi> yet whoever conſiders, that they were many times given for <hi>many Hundred years;</hi> nay, as the Doctor has it, for many <hi>Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years to come;</hi> he muſt ſoon conclude, that this could not be giving <hi>Leave to ſin</hi> for ſo long time to come, which ſo far ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds the term of Mans Life: but only the Releaſing of <hi>Penan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> which being aſſign'd in proportion to the Sins, for ſome Sins, <hi>Three</hi> years Penance; for others, <hi>Five;</hi> for others, <hi>Seven;</hi> might with ſome careleſs Chriſtians amount to that degree, that for <hi>Fifty years of Life,</hi> they might poſſibly have <hi>Five thouſand years Penalties</hi> due to their Sins. This is it then we underſtand by <hi>Indulgences</hi> or <hi>Pardons,</hi> not a <hi>Leave</hi> or <hi>Liberty to ſin;</hi> nay, not the <hi>Forgiveneſs of Sins;</hi> but only a <hi>Diſcharge</hi> from the <hi>Canonical Penances:</hi> which is very far from what the Doctor inſinuates into his Auditory, which, as propos'd by
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:65446:33"/> him, We acknowledge, is a Practice Unjuſtifiable: and if any Prelates in our Church, have formerly made an unjuſt <hi>Gain</hi> of <hi>Indulgences,</hi> we as little approve it as the Doctor: For tho' we may lawfully juſtifie all good <hi>Practices,</hi> yet for <hi>Abuſes,</hi> let thoſe Anſwer that were concern'd in them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="character">
               <head>Thirteenth Character of a Pulpit-Papiſt.</head>
               <argument>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <note n="1" place="margin">N. Bisby.</note> 
                        <hi>IF he be Falſe and Deceitful to Mankind, yet</hi> Euge bone ſerve, <hi>all is well, and he in an inſtant is thought worthy of a better Kingdom.</hi> 
                        <note n="2" place="margin">Hickering.</note> 
                        <hi>No Man can be a Papiſt, but he whoſe Eyes are blinded by Education, or he who puts his own Eyes out by Atheiſm.</hi> 
                        <note n="3" place="margin">Dr. Fowler.</note> 
                        <hi>His Council of</hi> Trent <hi>expreſſeth its allowance of Picturing the Divinity it ſelf; and accordingly Pictures of the Bleſſed Trinity (O Hateful Sight) are ordinarily to be beheld in Popiſh Churches.</hi> 
                        <note n="4" place="margin">Apol. for the Pulpit.</note> 
                        <hi>He Prays to Images.</hi> 
                        <note n="5" place="margin">D. Fowler</note> 
                        <hi>He Worſhips the Bread and Wine, not as Repreſentations of God, but as God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi> 
                        <note n="6" place="margin">D. Fowler</note> 
                        <hi>He is taught, that the Paſſion of Chriſt takes away only the Guilt of Mortal Sins, not their Eternal Puniſhment.</hi> 
                        <note n="7" place="margin">D. Fowler</note> 
                        <hi>Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Non-neceſſity of Repentance before the Imminent Point of Death.</hi> 
                        <note n="8" place="margin">D. Fowler</note> 
                        <hi>And that the bare ſaying of Prayers, without either minding what he ſays, or underſtanding it, is ſufficient to the Divine Acceptance.</hi> 
                        <note n="9" place="margin">Dr. Hooper. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>So is he to appear before God dumb and ſenſleſs, like one of his Idols.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </argument>
               <p>In theſe Colours were the <hi>Papiſts</hi> Repreſented from the <hi>Pulpit</hi> by theſe Preachers, in the Year 1681. when the time was, not of confuting them by <hi>Goſpel</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> but by bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſly knocking them in the Head like Beaſts. But all theſe Colours are either Falſe or Deceitful, as might be eaſily ſhewn at large; but I am quite tir'd, as I fear, the Reader is too, by ſtaying ſo long in this nauſcous Stuff. I'll therefore paſs them over, as ſuch <hi>Calumnies</hi> deſerve, with as ſhort a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection as may be, but yet in order. And therefore as to the <hi>Firſt,</hi> it is abſolutely Falſe; for <hi>Falſhood</hi> and <hi>Deceit</hi> are no where recommended or taught by his <hi>Church,</hi> and are ſo far from ſitting Men for Heaven, that I am certain, no Man, of what Church ſoever, guilty of thoſe wicked Qualities, can
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:65446:34"/> poſſibly have admittance there, till they have firſt diſcharg'd their <hi>Conſcience</hi> by a ſincere <hi>Repentance,</hi> and made <hi>Reſtitution</hi> to the <hi>Parties Injur'd</hi> to the beſt of their power. This is the <hi>Receiv'd Doctrin</hi> of his Church: and I hope in their Dealing, they practiſe it as much as any. I don't queſtion, but there are ſtill Knaves of his Communion; but then let that Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, who has no ſuch of his Coat, or in his Church, come and ſling the firſt Stone.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Second</hi> is Falſe too; ſince 'tis known, that there are great numbers of <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who were never ſo by <hi>Education.</hi> And is it not an abominable and wicked Slander, to accuſe all ſuch of <hi>Atheiſm;</hi> and that had it not been for their blinding themſelves by this, they had never become <hi>Papiſts?</hi> Since ſuch as have made the Obſervation, find, that thoſe, who were of a good Life when <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> continue to be ſo when <hi>Papiſts:</hi> and that many, who liv'd like <hi>Atheiſts</hi> when <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</hi> become <hi>better Chriſtians</hi> by being <hi>Papiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Third</hi> is likewiſe Falſe; ſince the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> do's not allow the <hi>Picturing</hi> the <hi>Divinity it ſelf,</hi> as the <hi>Preacher</hi> ſays; but takes particular care, <hi>if it happen</hi> (ſays the Council) <hi>that the Hiſtories of the Holy Scripture be Painted or Figur'd, that the People be taught, that the Divinity is not therefore Figur'd or Painted, as if that could be ſeen with Corporeal Eyes, or repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in Colours.</hi> Seſſ. 25. which is juſt contrary to what the Preacher delivers. And therefore tho' ſometimes in our Churches there may be ſeen <hi>Figures,</hi> to put us in mind of the Bleſſed <hi>Trinity;</hi> yet the like may be ſeen too in the Frontiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece of ſome <hi>Bibles</hi> and <hi>Common-Prayer-Books</hi> of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> to which the Preacher's Exclamation of <hi>O Hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Sight!</hi> may be as properly apply'd as to any thing of that nature in our Churches.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Fourth,</hi> of <hi>Praying to Images,</hi> is falſe too; for we are taught to <hi>Pray</hi> to none but <hi>God alone;</hi> and to deſire the <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion</hi> or <hi>Prayers</hi> of ſuch holy Perſons, as are acceptable to God, whether in Heaven or Earth: Theſe, we own, may be aſſiſting to us, by the Prayers they offer up to the Throne of God: where St. <hi>John</hi> ſaw an <hi>Angel offering Incenſe with the Prayers of all the Saints upon the Golden Altar, which was before the Throne.</hi> Revel. 8. 3. But for <hi>Images,</hi> we confeſs them to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:65446:34"/> be nothing but <hi>Wood</hi> or <hi>Stone,</hi> &amp;c. that they can neither Hear, See, nor Underſtand; they are of ſome uſe indeed, inaſmuch as they are <hi>Sacred Remembrances</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> or his <hi>Saints;</hi> but are ſtill devoid of all <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Helping</hi> or <hi>Praying</hi> for us. And we acknowledge it a like Abſurdity, to <hi>Pray to an Image,</hi> as to offer a <hi>Petition</hi> to the <hi>Statue</hi> of the King. The <hi>Apologizer</hi> has found an odd Notion, <hi>pag.</hi> 32. of <hi>leaving Prayers with an Image:</hi> which I ſuppoſe is the ſame, as <hi>leaving ones Grace in a Hat,</hi> when a Man <hi>gives Thanks</hi> with that before his <hi>Mouth</hi> and his <hi>Eyes.</hi> And if this be his meaning of our <hi>Praying to Images,</hi> I wiſh he would expound it ſo to his Hearers at his next Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, otherwiſe I ſhall ſtill take him for a <hi>Miſrepreſenter.</hi> If I charg'd any thing farther than due, in relation to this Point, in the <hi>Advice to the Pulpits,</hi> I ask the Preacher's Pardon, reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to do him all the Right he ſhall require; for I aſſure him, 'twas nothing of <hi>Deſign,</hi> but <hi>Miſtake</hi> only: and therefore <hi>I</hi> do not here ſet this Calumny under his Name, but quote the <hi>Apologizer,</hi> who both <hi>aſſerts,</hi> and pretends to <hi>defend</hi> it. And I wiſh the <hi>Pulpits</hi> would do us the ſame Right, in retracting and owning the many Wrongs they have done us, if Repenting be not beneath their Station.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Fifth</hi> is Falſe; ſince we worſhip only <hi>God himſelf,</hi> and not the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> which we believe not to be in the B. Sacrament. And therefore this Charge is to be reckon'd for <hi>Miſrepreſenting,</hi> by the Judgment of a former Adverſary, who gives this Sentence: <hi>If we put our own Opinions of his</hi> (a Papiſts) <hi>Faith and Practice into his Character, this</hi> (ſays he) <hi>is Miſrepreſenting; becauſe a Papiſt has not the ſame Opinion of theſe things, which we have, and this makes it a falſe Character. Anſw. to Pap. Prot. pag.</hi> 17. Let the <hi>Apologizer</hi> examin this Rule, and ſee whether it be not our Caſe, whilſt the <hi>Preacher</hi> gives a Character of us, not according to <hi>ours,</hi> but <hi>his own</hi> Belief.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Sixth</hi> is Falſe; for tho' we confeſs a <hi>Temporal Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> ſometimes to remain due to Sin, after the <hi>Guilt</hi> is remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; yet the <hi>Eternal Puniſhment</hi> is releas'd, through the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of the ſame Cauſe by which the <hi>Guilt</hi> is diſcharg'd, to wit, the <hi>Paſſion of Chriſt:</hi> and whatſoever Satisfaction we at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to <hi>Human Means,</hi> yet nothing of this can find ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:65446:35"/> or prevail with God, but through the help of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Grace, and the Merits of Chriſt our Redeemer, who gave himſelf a <hi>General Ranſom</hi> for the World, and yet requires we ſhould <hi>apply</hi> it to our ſelves; which <hi>Application of ours</hi> do's not at all derogate from the <hi>Plenitude</hi> of Chriſt's <hi>Satisfaction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Seventh</hi> is abſolutely contrary to the Doctrin and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Practice of our Church, whoſe Members do generally go to <hi>Confeſſion</hi> many times in the Year, and are under an <hi>Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of doing it at leaſt <hi>Once</hi> a Year, which cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, as is directed by our Spiritual Books, but by a <hi>Sincere</hi> and <hi>Hearty Repentance:</hi> how then is the <hi>Non-neceſſity of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance before the Imminent Point of Death,</hi> a Doctrin of <hi>ours;</hi> when all in our Communion are bound by <hi>Precept,</hi> not to defer it paſt the Year? All our Divines indeed own <hi>Repentance</hi> to be <hi>abſolutely neceſſary</hi> at the <hi>Point of Death;</hi> but that it is <hi>not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary till then,</hi> I am certain is contrary both to the Receiv'd Doctrin of our Church, and the Practice of her Profeſſors. And tho' we acknowledge, that a <hi>Hearty Repentance</hi> even at the Point of Death, is accepted by God, according to that, <hi>At whatſoever hour a Sinner Repents,</hi> &amp;c. Yet this is not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly'd on: and we hear nothing ſo much diſcourag'd in our Books and Sermons, as deferring Repentance to the laſt; there being but <hi>One,</hi> as S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> obſerves, throughout the whole Scripture, who <hi>truly Repented</hi> at the <hi>hour of Death,</hi> to wit, the <hi>Good Thief.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Eighth</hi> is again contrary to our Doctrin: in all our Prayers, we being directed to preſerve an <hi>Actual</hi> and <hi>Lively</hi> Attention: and the admitting <hi>voluntary Diſtractions</hi> at <hi>Prayers,</hi> being one of the <hi>Sins,</hi> of which every one that goes to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion,</hi> is to make Examination, and to accuſe himſelf; as may be ſeen in all our Books, that give Inſtructions in order to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</hi> But it ſeems, by the <hi>Apologizer,</hi> this <hi>Saying</hi> of the <hi>Preacher</hi> is not charg'd upon us, as a <hi>Profeſs'd Doctrin</hi> of ours, but only as a <hi>Conſequence</hi> of his own Head: and from whence do's he draw it? From this ſuppos'd <hi>Principle,</hi> viz. <hi>The Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church enjoyns the ſaying them</hi> (Prayers) <hi>in a Language un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to the Generality of the People;</hi> which too is none of the Trueſt: for this is not enjoyn'd by our Church, to thoſe that <hi>ſay Prayers:</hi> For the <hi>Prieſts</hi> ſaying theirs in <hi>Latin,</hi> underſtand
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:65446:35"/> what they ſay: and the <hi>People</hi> have Theirs in their <hi>own Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage,</hi> as may be ſeen in our <hi>Manuals,</hi> and in our <hi>Chappels;</hi> where in the Hands of the <hi>People</hi> may be found <hi>Prayer-Books</hi> as <hi>Different</hi> in <hi>Language,</hi> as thoſe that uſe them are Different in <hi>Nation.</hi> And tho' the <hi>Maſs</hi> be ſaid in <hi>Latin,</hi> yet 'tis only as the Function of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> who underſtand it: The People have the ſame in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and are inſtructed to accompany the Prieſt with Devotion, and be attentive to every <hi>Myſtery</hi> of the <hi>Oblation:</hi> Which being a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> rather than a <hi>Form of Prayer,</hi> the <hi>Attention</hi> and <hi>Devotion,</hi> in reſpect to the <hi>People,</hi> do's not fo much conſiſt in the <hi>Words</hi> ſaid by the Prieſt, as in what is <hi>done</hi> by him: as the <hi>Devotion</hi> of thoſe Devout Women and other Believers upon <hi>Mount Calvary,</hi> in the time of the Paſſion, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended more upon being Attentive to what Chriſt <hi>Suffered,</hi> and the <hi>Sacrifice he offer'd</hi> for the Redemption of the World, than upon the <hi>Words</hi> that he ſpoke, which were not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther underſtood, as the Scripture aſſures us, by the Standers by. In the ſame manner therefore as we ſhould have been <hi>Attentive</hi> upon <hi>Mount Calvary,</hi> we are <hi>Attentive</hi> here in this <hi>Oblation,</hi> that is made upon the Altar, of the Body and Blood of Chriſt: and whoſoever is at the time of this Service, <hi>Dumb and Senſleſs like an Idol,</hi> (which is the <hi>Ninth</hi> Calumny) muſt be neceſſarily as ſenſleſs as an <hi>Idol;</hi> ſince a <hi>True Believer,</hi> who has a Right <hi>Faith</hi> and Apprehenſion of this <hi>Myſtery,</hi> can no more be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at it without Devotion, than he could have ſtood un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd under the Croſs, while his Redeemer hung upon it. The <hi>Jews</hi> indeed were ſo then, and may be now, and all thoſe who are like them, <hi>without Faith;</hi> but for a <hi>True Believer,</hi> 'tis impoſſible. But the Matter of <hi>Fact</hi> is the beſt Confutation of this Slanderous <hi>Conſequence;</hi> whilſt any one that takes a view of our People in time of <hi>Maſs,</hi> will find them with as much <hi>Devotion</hi> and <hi>Attention,</hi> that is, as much unlike <hi>Idols,</hi> as <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> are generally at their <hi>Common-Prayer.</hi> So that all this is nothing but a Deduction grounded upon <hi>Ignorance,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently a <hi>Calumny,</hi> inſtead of a <hi>True Character</hi> of us: but I fear whilſt the <hi>Vindicator</hi> makes the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> an Abettor of ſuch unreaſonable Doctrin, 'tis not the effect of Ignorance only, but ſomething worſe: For tho his Aſſertion be, That <hi>Prayers may be ſaid Well and Devoutly, without attending to the Words or Senſe of</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:65446:36"/> 
                  <hi>the Prayers, B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T RATHER P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RELY ON GOD:</hi> which laſt Words are fairly left out by the <hi>Vindicator;</hi> yet whoſoever conſiders this, will not find this makes any thing for that <hi>Careleſs</hi> and <hi>Indevout</hi> way of Praying, which is here by the Preacher charg'd upon the <hi>Papiſts.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="character">
               <head>Fourteenth Character of a Pulpit-Papiſt.</head>
               <argument>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <note n="1" place="margin">Dr. Hooper.</note> 
                        <hi>TO cover his Idolatry, he commits Sacrilege, ſteals away one of the Ten Commandments, and by the</hi> Index Expurga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torius <hi>blots the Two Tables themſelves.</hi> 
                        <note n="2" place="margin">Dr. Wallis.</note> 
                        <hi>For his Abſolution 'tis not neceſſary he ſhould be ſorry for his Sin, but only for the Penance.</hi> 
                        <note n="3" place="margin">Id.</note> 
                        <hi>And if this ſhould fail, 'tis but being at the Charge of an Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence or Pope's Pardon; that is, to purchaſe ſo many Penyworth of other Men's Merit: and this is what is requir'd by way of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, inſtead of Regeneration, Sanctification, Holineſs and a Godly Life.</hi> 
                        <note n="4" place="margin">B. E.</note> 
                        <hi>Auricular Confeſſion, their great Intelligencer and Lieger-Nuncio, is the main Curb of the Laity, whereby the Clergy hold them in awe, in being admitted to all the Secrets of States and Families, thereby to work their Purpoſes and Plots: 'tis a Matter of meer Intereſt, and were there no Gain in it, they would be aſham'd of it.</hi> 
                        <note n="5" place="margin">Id.</note> 
                        <hi>Ignorance is the Mother of their Devotion, which they are bound to by Vow, and under the ſevereſt Penalties.</hi> 
                        <note n="6" place="margin">Dr. Sharp.</note> 
                        <hi>They muſt wholly ſubmit their Reaſon to an Infallible Judge, even ſo far (if one of their greateſt Authors ſay true) to be bound to believe Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue to be Bad, and Vice to be Good, if it ſhall pleaſe his Holineſs to ſay ſo.</hi> 
                        <note n="7" place="margin">Dr. Butler.</note> 
                        <hi>Their Church-men muſt live a Single Life, whether Honeſtly or no, it makes no matter.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </argument>
               <p>In this manner was the <hi>Papiſt</hi> deſcrib'd in the Years 1678, 79, 81, 82. All <hi>Plotting</hi> Years; Years wherein <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty</hi> acted but very ſmall Parts, and were not for the Turn; and I fear, had not that free acceſs to the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> at leaſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mix'd from Paſſion and Prejudice, as became Preachers of the Goſpel. This Character may ſerve for Inſtance, in which the <hi>Firſt</hi> Charge is not ſincere; ſince 'tis known, that <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lics</hi> have the <hi>Ten Commandments</hi> in their <hi>Bibles</hi> and <hi>Catechiſms:</hi> and if they are ſet in <hi>ſhort</hi> in ſome little <hi>Abſtracts</hi> of Chriſtian
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:65446:36"/> Doctrin, in compliance to the weakneſs of ſome Memories and Capacities; yet his is far from what the Preacher ſays, of <hi>Stealing away one of the Commandments;</hi> ſince this that they do to One of them, they do to more, ſetting down <hi>only</hi> the Words of the <hi>Precept,</hi> without the Addition of <hi>Threats, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes,</hi> or <hi>Explications,</hi> as may be obſerv'd in the <hi>Firſt, Second, Third</hi> and <hi>Fourth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Second</hi> is like this: For that Sorrow which the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Trent</hi> requires for Abſolution, includes a <hi>Deteſtation of the Sins committed, and a Firm Purpoſe of not Sinning for the time to come,</hi> as may be ſeen <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 14. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. and this, I think, is little leſs than Contradictions to the Saying of the Preacher.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Third</hi> involves an <hi>Abſolute Falſity,</hi> whilſt it ſuppoſes, that a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> who is ſorry neither for his <hi>Sins,</hi> nor the <hi>Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> that attends them, has no more to do, than to procure or buy a <hi>Pope's Pardon;</hi> and that this is ſufficient for him, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of <hi>Repentance, Amendment,</hi> and a <hi>Holy Life.</hi> This is a moſt abominable Doctrin in it ſelf, and moſt injuriouſly charg'd upon us in theſe words <hi>(This is what they require)</hi> by which the Preacher inſinuates it into his Hearers, as a thing approv'd by our Church. Which is ſo far from being True, that the only ground for it, appears only in the <hi>Practice</hi> of ſome profligate Men; which is a way of <hi>Repreſenting,</hi> that if follow'd, will draw even the <hi>Infinite Mercy</hi> of God under the ſame Scandal; there being not wanting many Chriſtians, who preſuming up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on This, continue on in their Wickedneſs without Remorſe.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Fourth</hi> is a moſt odious Character of an Inſtitution allow'd even in the Church of <hi>England;</hi> a meer piece of <hi>Drol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery,</hi> and a Demonſtration of the admirable skill theſe Men have, in making the beſt of things Ridiculous. And what wonder, that We are ſet out thus <hi>Black</hi> and <hi>Deform'd</hi> by them, who have no more reſpect for their own <hi>Church,</hi> than thus to expoſe, what ſhe approves? But of this we have ſpoke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Fifth</hi> is a great Calumny, and only an empty <hi>Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence</hi> of the Preacher, inſtead of what we <hi>Profeſs.</hi> And tho' the Apologizer pretends to make it out, <hi>viz. That we are bound to Ignorance by Vow;</hi> and inſtances in the <hi>Monks, Friers,</hi> and other <hi>Religious</hi> Men; yet every <hi>Library</hi> in the Chriſtian
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:65446:37"/> World, is an evident Confutation of this weak Pretence, whilſt the greateſt part of Books of all ſort of Learning, that are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, have thoſe very Men for their Authors, who are thus confidently aſſerted, as <hi>bound to Ignorance by Vow.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Sixth</hi> is a moſt groſs Abuſe of <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> who do's not ſay that <hi>We are bound to believe Vertue to be Bad, and Vice to be Good, if it ſhall pleaſe his Holineſs to ſay ſo,</hi> as the Preacher po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively declares; but on the contrary defends, that <hi>'tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for the Pope ſo to Err, as to declare Vertue to be Bad, and Vice to be Good,</hi> it being his Opinion that he is thus <hi>Infallible.</hi> This is the <hi>Doctrin</hi> this Author abſolutely ſtands to and proves: the former words of the Preacher are only us'd by <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> not as his <hi>Aſſertion,</hi> but only as an <hi>Inconvenience,</hi> which he ſays would follow, if this Doctrin of his were not true: Juſt as if I to prove, that the Scripture cannot <hi>Err</hi> in <hi>Commanding Vice,</hi> or <hi>Forbidding Vertue,</hi> ſhould thus argue: If the Scripture could thus <hi>Err</hi> in <hi>Commanding Vice,</hi> or <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding Vertue,</hi> we ſhould be bound to believe <hi>Vertue to be Bad,</hi> and <hi>Vice to be Good,</hi> becauſe we are bound to believe that to be <hi>Bad</hi> which the <hi>Scripture Forbids,</hi> and that <hi>Good</hi> which it <hi>Commands:</hi> And what Abſurdity in thus arguing <hi>ab Inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nienti,</hi> when I have before poſitively aſſerted, that 'tis impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible it ſhould ſo Err? And yet this is our Caſe, in which the Preacher moſt abuſively and falſly ſets out the <hi>Inconvenience,</hi> from which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> argues for his <hi>Concluſion</hi> or <hi>Doctrin,</hi> which is a moſt inexcuſable Aſperſion. I deſire the Reader to examin this Place of <hi>Bellarmine (De Rom. Pont. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 5.) to diſcover which Side is to be condemn'd; whether <hi>Bellarmine</hi> of <hi>Impiety,</hi> or the <hi>Preacher</hi> of <hi>Forgery:</hi> and this becauſe I find this ſame thing urg'd againſt <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> not only in this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, but likewiſe in others, and by our preſent <hi>Apologizer</hi> too, <hi>pag.</hi> 30.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Seventh</hi> is utterly Falſe, it being no <hi>indifferent</hi> thing in our Church, whether the <hi>Clergy</hi> live <hi>Honeſtly,</hi> or <hi>not;</hi> ſince for them to live <hi>not Honeſtly,</hi> is certainly a moſt grievous Sin, no leſs than <hi>Sacrilege.</hi> And is it indifferent, whether they Sin or no? The <hi>Apologizer</hi> dares not undertake to make this good; and therefore he falls much below the <hi>Preacher,</hi> pretending only, that <hi>more care</hi> is taken that they live <hi>Singly,</hi> than that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:65446:37"/> they live <hi>Honeſtly;</hi> and this chiefly, becauſe the <hi>Puniſhment</hi> for a Clergy-man that <hi>Marries,</hi> is much greater, than for one that keeps his <hi>Concubine.</hi> Which is as much to the purpoſe, as if I ſhould ſay, that according to the Principles of the <hi>Church of England, it matters not, whether her Members turn Turks, or no;</hi> And then ſhould bring this for Proof; becauſe ſhe has <hi>ſevere Penalties,</hi> even of <hi>Death</hi> it ſelf, for ſuch as become <hi>Papiſts,</hi> but none at all for thoſe that turn <hi>Turks:</hi> And becauſe 'tis thus evident, that ſhe takes <hi>more care</hi> in the <hi>One Caſe</hi> than in the <hi>Other;</hi> Is this enough to juſtifie a <hi>Preacher,</hi> in declaring, that the <hi>Church of England</hi> is careful indeed to preſerve her Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors from <hi>Popery;</hi> but whether they <hi>turn Turks or not,</hi> with her <hi>it matters not?</hi> Yet this is the Method of ſetting out the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in their true Colours, and if you challenge them of <hi>Miſrepreſenting,</hi> they take it ill forſooth, and with the <hi>Woman</hi> in the <hi>Proverbs, c.</hi> 30. wipe their Mouths, and then ask, <hi>What Evil have we done?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For my part, I cannot tell what Evil they intend, or how far their <hi>Intereſt</hi> or <hi>Paſſion</hi> puts them upon Arguing in defiance to their own Conſcience: but this I am certain, that they moſt groſly abuſe us, in ſetting us out thus <hi>Black</hi> and <hi>Odious</hi> to their Hearers, upon ſuch Imaginary Grounds, and the vain Conſtructions of their own prejudic'd Phancies: which are ſo fertil in producing <hi>Conſequences,</hi> ſuch as are ſerviceable to their Turn, that I cannot imagine any thing of Chriſtianity ſo <hi>Perfect</hi> and <hi>Complete</hi> in it ſelf beyond Exception, as to be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of ſtanding the Teſt of this <hi>Church-of-England-Method</hi> of <hi>True Repreſenting.</hi> The Reader may have obſerv'd in the peruſal of theſe <hi>Characters,</hi> and more at large in the <hi>Advice to the Pulpits,</hi> what ways they have to run down <hi>Innocence</hi> with <hi>Applauſe</hi> and <hi>Triumph:</hi> What fly <hi>Inſinuations</hi> and pretty <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences</hi> they make uſe of, to work the People into the <hi>Belief</hi> of what they pleaſe: How ſafely they can <hi>Practice,</hi> what they are actually <hi>condemning</hi> in their Neighbor: What excellent <hi>Turns</hi> they can give to Authors, bend a <hi>Text</hi> to the beſt Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage: <hi>Gloſs</hi> to Admiration, make the moſt <hi>Sacred</hi> things look <hi>Prophane</hi> and <hi>Ridiculous.</hi> Theſe and many other ſuch Sleights and little Arts may be ſeen in theſe <hi>Inſtances</hi> and <hi>Characters,</hi> which are ſo unjuſtifiable upon this ſcore, that I profeſs I
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:65446:38"/> would not be guilty of dealing thus <hi>unjuſtly,</hi> or <hi>wronging</hi> even the moſt <hi>undeſerving</hi> of Neighbors in this nature, for a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Worlds; ſince, I am ſatisfied, I muſt firſt lay aſide Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and the thoughts of Salvation, before I could enter upon ſo unwarrantable an Engagement. I do not here accuſe any Adverſaries of <hi>knowingly</hi> incurring this Guilt; but I fear <hi>Education, innate Animoſity, Intereſt</hi> or other <hi>Paſſion,</hi> ſo far biaſſes their Judgment, as to make the moſt Unreaſonable of Methods appear to them Juſt and Reaſonable. All that I'll ſay at preſent is, that if to be a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> is to be that which is here deſcrib'd in theſe <hi>Characters,</hi> that then certainly to be a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> is to be the <hi>Worſt of Men;</hi> that 'tis but Juſt the <hi>Pulpit's</hi> ſhould expoſe his <hi>Errors</hi> and <hi>Abominations,</hi> and the People hate and deteſt them: and that 'tis ſo far from being a doubt whether he be a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> that 'tis certain he can be <hi>none:</hi> and that if he be bound to <hi>Believe</hi> and <hi>Live</hi> according to the <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> here laid down, he can have no Right to Salvation.</p>
               <p>And of this I deſire the <hi>Defender</hi> of the <hi>State of the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie</hi> to take notice, that in this I anſwer his <hi>Challenge;</hi> and here do declare to him, that theſe <hi>Doctrins</hi> as here ſet down by his Fellow Miniſters, and charg'd upon the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> I do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and abominate: and that ſince to be a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> according to the Notion of the <hi>Pulpits,</hi> is to believe according to the Form aſſerted in <hi>their Characters,</hi> I would be a <hi>Turk</hi> as ſoon as <hi>their Papiſt.</hi> This Declaration I make for his Satisfaction, ſince he deſires it; and if it be the thing I ought to have done, as he ſays, I here do it now, if this will end the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie; but I muſt caution him to be a little more Reaſonable, than when he made the late Reſolution, of thinking nothing to be deteſtable amongſt all the Doctrins laid to us, beſides ſuch as I expreſly reject; ſince 'tis impoſſible I ſhould ever ſum them up, there being ſcarce a <hi>Sermon</hi> or <hi>Book</hi> of theirs, but what furniſhes freſh Matter; and like <hi>ill Weeds,</hi> grow every day: however, if he'll but ſend me word, when the <hi>Guides</hi> of his Church are become ſuch Lovers of <hi>Sincerity</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> as to leave off <hi>Calumniating</hi> and <hi>throwing Dirt</hi> againſt us, I ſhall then be in ſome hopes of bringing the <hi>Deteſtable Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrins</hi> into Number; but till then, he muſt never expect to ſee it. And in the mean time, I deſire him to draw me up an
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:65446:38"/> exact Catalogue of <hi>all</hi> and <hi>every Sin,</hi> by which the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are broken; if he'll but offer at this, he may fall ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing into the account of the unreaſonable Task he has put upon me.</p>
               <p>By this time I hope the Reader is ſatisfi'd, that 'tis not without Reaſon the <hi>Papiſts</hi> complain of being <hi>Miſrepreſented;</hi> and tho' ſome have had the Confidence, to pretend that we have not produc'd <hi>One clear Inſtance</hi> of it, yet that now we have <hi>Many,</hi> and <hi>Many more</hi> they may have, if it be requir'd. And this, I hope, is ſufficient to put an end to <hi>one half</hi> of the Controverſie, which was the Subject of the <hi>Firſt Book,</hi> to wit, that the <hi>Papiſt is Miſrepreſented:</hi> And if any make Exceptions againſt the Character of him thus diſguis'd, as 'twas drawn <hi>there,</hi> I'll never quarrel upon that ſcore; let that be ras'd out, and theſe others take the Place, which 'tis likely are more Authentic.</p>
               <p>As for the other Part, to wit, of the <hi>Papiſt Repreſented,</hi> I here own it again, that it is the <hi>Papiſt I am;</hi> and whoever aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents to that Character, in that very Form, has done what is requir'd, as to thoſe Particulars, to be made a Member of our Communion. This Offer may be ſaid to have been Anſwer'd over and over: But the Matter of <hi>Fact</hi> defeats all thoſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, and is a Demonſtration, that they are nothing but Shuffling: For whilſt a Man may be receiv'd upon thoſe <hi>Terms,</hi> and yet cannot be receiv'd unleſs he aſſents to the <hi>Faith</hi> of the Church, 'tis evident, that in that Character the <hi>Faith</hi> of the Church is <hi>Truly Repreſented.</hi> Our new Adverſary has one Cavil here to put in, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Character of the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt Repreſented,</hi> is not a good Character, becauſe the Faith of a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> as ſtated under each Article, is not <hi>All</hi> his Faith. And may not he, upon the ſame ſcore, reject the Goſpel of S. <hi>John,</hi> for being no <hi>True Goſpel;</hi> becauſe it do's not contain <hi>All</hi> that <hi>Jeſus</hi> did or ſpoke? If it be <hi>true,</hi> as far as it goes, and recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the moſt Conſiderable of thoſe Miſtakes, and prejudic'd Opinions, which are either deſignedly or ignorantly laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Catholics,</hi> it do's as much as was intended by it: but to think, that it ought to reach to every Particular, was more than ever I could pretend to. And to this Difficulty I deſire this <hi>Anſwerer</hi> to let me know his Opinion of the <hi>Expoſition of</hi>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:65446:39"/> 
                  <hi>the Doctrins of the Church of England,</hi> whether it contains un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der each Article, <hi>All</hi> that is of <hi>Faith</hi> in that Church? and whether if any thing be omitted, it is to paſs for a <hi>Miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Trick,</hi> as 'tis here term'd? But this Man has ſtill ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Scruple, <hi>pag.</hi> 33. That if he ſhould come into our Church upon the Terms I have propos'd, whether I will be Security, that <hi>he ſhall not be preſs'd to profeſs and practice that Popery, which I have either deny'd or conceal'd.</hi> Marry, if he means by that <hi>Popery,</hi> the <hi>Pulpit-Popery,</hi> a part of which is ſet down in the Characters above, I'll give him the ſame Security I have my ſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt promis'd to his Church,</hi> which will never permit it to lead her Members into ſuch Abominations: he may have the Security too of a <hi>good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> which cannot be <hi>preſs'd</hi> to the profeſſion of ſo much Evil. And in this he may ſee his other material Queſtion An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd, <hi>pag.</hi> 34. <hi>Whether he may be admitted into our Communion, with that which he calls Old Popery?</hi> For if his <hi>Old Popery</hi> be the <hi>Pulpit-Pulpery,</hi> he ſees we reject it: and I tell him, that whatſoever Church would receive him, with the <hi>Profeſſion</hi> of <hi>all thoſe Scandalous Doctrins</hi> the <hi>Pulpits</hi> charge againſt us, I would be ſure to be no Member of it; and if there were no other but that Church amongſt Chriſtians, I would then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to look towards <hi>Turky.</hi> And here this <hi>Anſwerer</hi> may now begin to perceive, how unſucceſsful he is in his laſt Trick, of endeavoring to make a Difference betwixt me and the Learned <hi>Vindicator</hi> of the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux,</hi> whilſt he now ſees, that the <hi>Popery</hi> I deteſt and abominate, is this <hi>Pulpit-Popery,</hi> as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd by the <hi>Parſons,</hi> in which there is ſo much of <hi>Inſincerity</hi> and <hi>Paſſionate Deductions,</hi> with other worſe ſort of Dealing, that I again own it to him, that I cannot but declare againſt it. I meddle not here with the <hi>Different Opinions</hi> of <hi>School-Divines,</hi> I leave them exerciſing their Wits in <hi>Speculations;</hi> but when a <hi>Parſon</hi> deſignedly enters amongſt thoſe <hi>Niceties,</hi> and picks out ſuch of them as he knows will look abſurd to his Auditory, and having play'd with them a while in the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> ſhewing all Sides but the <hi>Right,</hi> diſplaying them into moſt <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Conſequences,</hi> leaving the People to take all according to their own <hi>Vulgar Notions,</hi> without expounding to them the <hi>Senſe</hi> of the <hi>Schools;</hi> and after all concluding, <hi>Do you ſee what</hi>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:65446:39"/> 
                  <hi>the Papiſts Believe? Do you ſee what they Teach?</hi> Here I ſtep in, and cry out, <hi>Miſrepreſenting:</hi> whilſt 'tis by theſe Means inſinuated into the People, as if <hi>to be a Papiſt,</hi> were to <hi>believe all as they have laid it out in their Pulpits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for the rendring theſe kind of Religious Frauds Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſucceſsful, I in my Firſt Book, preſented the Reader with a View of the greateſt Part of our Doctrins, as <hi>Receiv'd</hi> and <hi>Profeſs'd</hi> in <hi>our Church:</hi> And in aſſigning Matters of <hi>Faith,</hi> I obſerv'd, not a different, but the ſame Rule with the <hi>Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator,</hi> whilſt I have declar'd nothing as an <hi>Article of our Belief,</hi> but what has been thus poſitively determin'd by the <hi>Church Repreſentative,</hi> or is ſo acknowledg'd by the whole <hi>Body Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſive,</hi> which is ſtill equivalent to it. And the currant paſſing of the Book, and general Reception of it amongſt <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lics,</hi> argued ſtrongly enough, that it was exact as to all this. But becauſe I deſign'd that Book for the Public, I did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent my ſelf with the bare ſtating ſuch our <hi>Avow'd Doctrins,</hi> or <hi>Articles of Faith;</hi> but I likewiſe added ſhort <hi>Expoſitions,</hi> in relation to ſome <hi>Proteſtant Objections</hi> generally made to each Article, of <hi>How can this be? Wherefore is this?</hi> &amp;c. And the <hi>Expoſitions</hi> I own to be <hi>no Articles of Faith,</hi> but only ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd Notions relating to the <hi>Articles</hi> of our <hi>Faith,</hi> as they are <hi>oppos'd</hi> by <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> or ſearch'd into by the <hi>Curious.</hi> And theſe were ſo far from being my Private Sentiments, that the Reader may find the ſame in our <hi>Ordinary Scripture-Catechiſms,</hi> of which there has been Printed, in this Nation in a few Years, not leſs than <hi>Twenty thouſand:</hi> And I hope ſo general a Rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption is ſufficient to juſtifie them againſt all Cavillers, and to convince any conſidering Men, that to Aſſent to the Catholic Faith, as ſo Expounded (which is ſo contrary to what <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> ſay, or to the <hi>Pulpit-Popery)</hi> is ſufficient for any Member of our Church. And if there be other ways of Expounding the ſame Articles, there's no Inconvenience in this; ſince where the <hi>Faith is the ſame,</hi> there may be variety of Opinions, as to the <hi>Hows</hi> or the <hi>Whys.</hi> And this, I hope, the Anſwerer will underſtand, if he pleaſe but to review <hi>The Expoſition of the Doctrin of the Church of England;</hi> in which, tho' the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor undertakes to propoſe <hi>That Form of Faith, that is openly profeſs'd and taught without any Diſguiſe or Diſſimulation</hi> in the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:65446:40"/> Church of <hi>England,</hi> as he ſays, <hi>Pref. pag. xvii.</hi> yet I fancy, amongſt thoſe Expoſitions, he'll find ſeveral <hi>Opinions</hi> of <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Doctors,</hi> inſtead of Points poſitively ſo determin'd by that Church: Let him but look over that a while, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve he may have as much reaſon to call in queſtion the <hi>Title</hi> of that Book, as that of the Biſhop; and that according to his way, I think, it ought to bear thus: <hi>An Expoſition of Some bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies Private Sentiments concerning the Doctrin of the Church of England.</hi> I leave him to conſider this a while; but I beg him to be Civil with the <hi>Author,</hi> and uſe him tenderly; for if he ſhould deal roughly with him, as he do's other his Adverſaries, and call him <hi>Madman</hi> or <hi>Fool,</hi> he might take it unkindly, and tell him, this do's not agree with his Coat. I believe 'tis bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter adviſe him, to take ſome other honeſt Employment, as to <hi>Dig,</hi> or make <hi>Almanacks,</hi> rather than write Controverſie: for this Gentleman can tell him, that to <hi>Impoſe upon Men in Books of Divinity,</hi> and to <hi>take a convenient Stand near the Town,</hi> is much alike for the Honeſty of the Undertaking. I expect he'll take ſome pains with him, ſince he is reſolv'd to ſpend no more of his time with the <hi>Vindicator</hi> or <hi>Repreſenter:</hi> Theſe, he ſays, are like to be <hi>Priviledg'd</hi> Perſons as to him, ſince he's reſolv'd to Anſwer them no more: they are not it ſeems ſo Good-na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur'd, as to be Confuted by him, and he takes it unkindly at their hands. But however, thoſe who know how <hi>abuſively</hi> he treats his Adverſaries, muſt needs take this for no ſmall <hi>Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege:</hi> And therefore We cannot but thank him for this his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, tho' late, of calling us <hi>Knaves</hi> or <hi>Fools</hi> no more. Which in his Language is the ſhort of his <hi>Making Replies.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:65446:40"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>THE Preface to the Reader.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Firſt Character of a Pulpit-Papiſt.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Pag.</hi> 13.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Second Character of a Pulpit-Papiſt.</cell>
                     <cell>15.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Third Character of a Pulpit-Papiſt.</cell>
                     <cell>16.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Fourth Character of a Pulpit-Papiſt.</cell>
                     <cell>19.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Fifth Character of a Pulpit-Papiſt.</cell>
                     <cell>25.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sixth Character of a Pulpit-Papiſt.</cell>
                     <cell>27.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Seventh Character of a Pulpit-Papiſt.</cell>
                     <cell>29.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Eighth Character of a Pulpit-Papiſt.</cell>
                     <cell>34.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ninth Character of a Pulpit-Papiſt.</cell>
                     <cell>35.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Tenth Character of a Pulpit-Papiſt.</cell>
                     <cell>38.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Eleventh Character of a Pulpit-Papiſt.</cell>
                     <cell>39.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Twelfth Character of a Pulpit-Papiſt.</cell>
                     <cell>42.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Thirteenth Character of a Pulpit-Papiſt.</cell>
                     <cell>45.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Fourteenth Character of a Pulpit-Papiſt.</cell>
                     <cell>50.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
